<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics on Mark Richman Consulting</title>
    <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/politics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Politics on Mark Richman Consulting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2009 15:45:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Conservative vs. Liberal</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/conservative-vs-liberal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2009 15:45:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/conservative-vs-liberal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If a conservative doesn&amp;#8217;t like guns, he doesn&amp;#8217;t buy one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a liberal doesn&amp;#8217;t like guns, he wants all guns outlawed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a conservative is a vegetarian, he doesn&amp;#8217;t eat meat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a liberal is a vegetarian, he wants all meat products banned for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a conservative sees a foreign threat, he thinks about how to defeat his enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A liberal wonders how to surrender gracefully and still look good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a conservative is homosexual, he quietly leads his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a liberal is homosexual, he demands legislated respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a black man or Hispanic are conservative, they see themselves as independently successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their liberal counterparts see themselves as victims in need of government protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a conservative is down-and-out, he thinks about how to better his situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A liberal wonders who is going to take care of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a conservative doesn&amp;#8217;t like a talk show host, he switches channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberals demand that those they don&amp;#8217;t like be shut down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a conservative is a non-believer, he doesn&amp;#8217;t go to church/temple/mosque.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A liberal non-believer wants any mention of G-d and religion silenced. (Unless it&amp;#8217;s a foreign religion, of course!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a conservative decides he needs health care, he goes about shopping for it, or may choose a job that provides it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A liberal demands that the rest of us pay for his.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a conservative slips and falls in a store, he gets up, laughs and is embarrassed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a liberal slips and falls, he grabs his neck, moans like he&amp;#8217;s in labor and then sues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a conservative reads this, he&amp;#8217;ll forward it so his friends can have a good laugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A liberal will delete it because he&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;offended.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>