<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marketing on Mark Richman Consulting</title>
    <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/marketing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Marketing on Mark Richman Consulting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 16:33:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/marketing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The CIO should become the CDO</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/the-cio-should-become-the-cdo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 16:33:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/the-cio-should-become-the-cdo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div&gt;
  The role of CIO as Chief &lt;em&gt;Infrastructure&lt;/em&gt; Officer is becoming increasingly irrelevant. IT budgets have shifted to Marketing. Corporate infrastructure is moving to the cloud. So what&amp;#8217;s left? &lt;strong&gt;Data&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-the-chief-data-officer&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enter the Chief Data Officer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Data belongs to the business, not just to IT. The CDO represents these business interests. If the CIO&amp;#8217;s job is simply to keep the lights on, that&amp;#8217;s not something the rest of the business will relate to. If CIOs are to survive, they must evolve, much like the technology for which they have been responsible.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Business intelligence, data analytics, and the value delivered to the business from SCAM (social, cloud, analytics, mobile) will become the primary driver of strategy. We already see this transformation occurring, and CMOs continue to wrestle away not only dollars, but also organizational ownership of the customer. The CMO becomes the CDO&amp;#8217;s best customer.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-cdo-is-a-hybrid-executive&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The CDO is a Hybrid Executive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The most effective CDO will be a &lt;i&gt;hybrid&lt;/i&gt; executive. Often graduating from a CIO or CTO role, their responsibilities will overlap several disciplines:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decision Management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Digital Transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The CDO is a transformational leader, driving business value by integrating emerging technologies with external marketing and customer facing initiatives with internal processes and applications.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-the-cio-can-thrive&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How the CIO can Thrive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The successful CIO will be the one who can take their organization and gear it toward the ability to program infrastructure as code, and serve new application development, driven by social, cloud, analytics, and mobile.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;challenge-questions-for-leaders&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge Questions for Leaders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What opportunities do you have for creating and enhancing the business value of data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your strategy for responding to SCAM (social, cloud, analytics, mobile) requirements of the business?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will you reshape the business to take advantage of data and technology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All Rights Reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Realtime Voice of the Customer</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/realtime-voice-of-the-customer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 16:04:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/realtime-voice-of-the-customer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been working with my best clients on integrating realtime Voice of the Customer (VoC) technologies into their e-commerce operations. The results have been enlightening and profitable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started with e-commerce systems around 2003, the industry was still in its infancy, and many customers still followed up online orders with multiple confirmation phone calls, or would use a vendor&amp;#8217;s website to get their phone number to place an order. This seems archaic now, just a few years later, when almost nobody picks up the phone to make a purchase. As e-commerce presences grew, the dual phone/web channels could not scale, so the direct and real time feedback of the customer was often lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we capture the Voice of the Customer, gather comments, and learn about opportunities for improvement if we don&amp;#8217;t speak to them anymore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E-commerce vendors developed email-based surveys to fill the gap left by waning telephone sales. These surveys are sent anywhere from the time of order confirmation to several days after delivery. The customer would complete the survey at their leisure, or not at all. Much of the shopping experience itself is usually out of mind by the time an email survey is completed. Over time, these have become little more than noise in a customer&amp;#8217;s inbox, and not very actionable by vendors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not particularly useful to capture the &lt;strong&gt;shopping experience&lt;/strong&gt; itself, email surveys are still effective in a couple of cases. Major vendors, Amazon included, use email surveys to solicit feedback on the products themselves, packaging quality, or shipping speed. Most customers, however, never fill these out unless there is something negative to report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we capture the essence of the customer&amp;#8217;s shopping experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exit Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more immediate feedback, exit surveys are usually placed on the order confirmation page, or when navigating away from this page. Customers&amp;#8217; shopping experience is still fresh in their mind, and both kudos and frustrations are more readily captured. This can also serve as an effective diagnostic tool for any technical problems with a website. I worked with one client, a $400M online retailer, to implement on-page exit surveys, and the results were astounding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their support number would occasionally ring with a customer complaint of checkout issues, only to have the order completed over the phone. This event would never get escalated to the web team for investigation. Over time, these problems just festered until a major promotion went out, when the phone rang nonstop due to shopping cart glitches. The exit survey was directed to the web team, not customer service, and issues were triaged in realtime. The root cause of the website issues was corrected, and &lt;strong&gt;conversion rate improved dramatically&lt;/strong&gt; in a week. No more hours wasted scratching your head over funnel abandon rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realtime Chat&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web-based realtime chat is a terrific innovation for customers to speak to a live person, and comfortably ask questions and give feedback where a phone call is inconvenient or time consuming. Some customers are shy, or have language issues, and typing is just easier for them. Unless you&amp;#8217;re particularly short staffed, this is a fantastic tool, and there&amp;#8217;s no downside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intercept Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I absolutely LOVE these. I use them on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my own website&lt;/a&gt;. Unlike email or exit surveys, you can get realtime feedback from visitors who &lt;strong&gt;chose not to buy&lt;/strong&gt;. These surveys typically take the form of a popup, and ask just a couple of key questions about the shopping experience. I also set them up to capture email addresses for lead generation. I&amp;#8217;ve also set them up to capture Net Promoter Score (NPS), demographic information, or to leak promotion codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often hear concerns about the intrusive nature of these popups, and whether or not they increase bounce rates. Better tools are typically more passive and configurable, appearing only at the most opportune time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we love hearing from customers who spent money, we also need to hear from those who don&amp;#8217;t. You&amp;#8217;re not going to get these insights any other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you hear your customers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amazon’s Outage and your Customers</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/amazons-outage-and-your-customers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 16:13:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/amazons-outage-and-your-customers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past Sunday around 6am ET, &lt;a href=&#34;http://aws.amazon.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Amazon Web Services&lt;/a&gt; had a mega outage, affecting millions of customers worldwide. Amazon Web Services (AWS) is Amazon&amp;#8217;s global cloud computing infrastructure business unit. AWS powers many popular websites including Netflix, Pinterest, Expedia, IMDB, Reddit, and more. Many of my own clients rely on AWS services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple AWS systems failed simultaneously: DynamoDB, Cognito, and CloudWatch. The latter, CloudWatch, is Amazon&amp;#8217;s own cloud monitoring platform. So, the system used to monitor their own cloud went offline, unable to alert on its offline status. Everyone assumed things were humming along until applications relying on AWS services began to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more Software-as-a-Service (SaaS) companies rely on cloud hosting providers like AWS for their infrastructure. When an outage strikes, it&amp;#8217;s not localized like the power company. The whole world feels it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One popular service in my area is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shipt.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Shipt&lt;/a&gt;, an on-demand grocery delivery service, which uses AWS. Customers were able to place orders, but never received their groceries. Shipt started receiving lots of angry Facebook messages, tweets, and emails. Nobody was manning the phones at 6am on a Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outage was resolved after several hours, but most end customers were unaware of the root cause of their favorite sites&amp;#8217; downtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think customers understand that websites can go down. They just don&amp;#8217;t want to be surprised. Sunday&amp;#8217;s event was about lack of information. When you have to Google news sites to see if a website or app is having problems, that&amp;#8217;s a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SaaS companies, like the ones affected by AWS&amp;#8217;s outage, are generally powerless to resolve underlying issues with their cloud provider. So, they need to be far more proactive in customer notification when problems arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s nothing more embarrassing and trust-killing than finding out from your customers that your website is having problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve implemented many third-party and custom monitoring solutions for my clients. One client, a $400M online retailer, had frequent issues with its infrastructure provider, and I delivered a monitoring solution that would notify the marketing team of outages. They could quickly get in front of the issue by posting a notice on the website of checkout issues, and were on call to respond to social media inquiries. This one change stopped most customer service calls, and rebuilt trust with customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acquiring new customers is far more expensive than keeping existing ones. Online businesses should focus on how proactively they handle outages. The customers will trust you and stick around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What steps are you taking to respond to outages and build trust?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Postscript: As I write this, Skype is offline globally most of the day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All Rights Reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Avoiding Executive Tech Turf Wars</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/avoiding-executive-tech-turf-wars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 22:44:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/avoiding-executive-tech-turf-wars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-712&#34; src=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/952-SS-execbox2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Executive Tech Turf War&#34; width=&#34;650&#34; height=&#34;397&#34; srcset=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/952-SS-execbox2-300x183.jpg 300w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/952-SS-execbox2.jpg 650w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Gartner predicted that CMOs would outspend CIOs by 2017. All signs continue to point to this reality, and the shift has created rifts between marketing and technology leaders. So, how do we avoid turf wars when it comes to marketing technology?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my best clients is a marketing executive at a medium-sized e-commerce company, who needed my help in selecting a vendor for her email marketing automation initiative. Her objectives were manifold: increase customer acquisition, customer retention, average order value, order frequency, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;avoid the IT department&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Avoid IT?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last couple of years, she felt like IT was a constant impediment when it came to adopting new marketing technologies and integrations with vendors. She said, “marketers want to grow and engage with customers quickly and often. We need to interact with customers across multiple channels, both online and offline &amp;#8211; proactively, reactively, and in realtime. The IT folks just get in the way!” I’ve heard sentiments like this countless times, both from clients and colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marketing and Shadow IT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As technology budgets shift from IT to marketing, so does the control over technology decisions. More and more, the CMO suite is driving the technology workload, and not the CIO. However, the IT department wants to retain control over the vendor selection process, integration efforts, process controls, and so on. Marketing sees this as an impediment to speed, and takes these functions on themselves, or ignores them altogether. What results is a gallimaufry of disparate systems, outside the purview of IT &amp;#8211; &lt;em&gt;Shadow IT.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turf War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, the CIO wants to retain control over the process and assets, and the CMO wants control over the vendor relationships and speed. Ultimately, the key to avoiding a turf war is a healthy relationship between the CIO and CMO. The CIO needs to respect the top-line growth responsibility of the CMO, enabling and supporting accordingly. Likewise the CMO needs to understand the potential security and compliance issues their Shadow IT can create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most successful clients understand that these relationships not only create good will between departments, but also create a culture of innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you guarding your turf or building bridges?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evangelizing Yourself</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/evangelizing-yourself/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2010 17:53:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/evangelizing-yourself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A phenomenally inspiring presentation by &lt;a title=&#34;Whitney Hess&#34; href=&#34;http://whitneyhess.com/blog/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Whitney Hess&lt;/a&gt; from IA Summit 2009. This really hits home for me, as I&amp;#8217;m also a self-promoting introvert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;__ss_1184852&#34; style=&#34;width: 425px; text-align: left;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt; 
  
  &lt;div style=&#34;font-size: 11px; font-family: tahoma,arial; height: 26px; padding-top: 2px;&#34;&gt;
    View more &lt;a style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34; href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/&#34;&gt;documents&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34; href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/whitneyhess&#34;&gt;Whitney Hess&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>101 Questions for Any Sales Situation</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/101-questions-for-any-sales-situation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2009 01:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/101-questions-for-any-sales-situation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;By Alan Weiss&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copyright 2009. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a title=&#34;101 Questions for Any Sales Situation&#34; href=&#34;http://www.contrarianconsulting.com/101-questions-for-any-sales-situation/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.contrarianconsulting.com/101-questions-for-any-sales-situation/&#34;&gt;http://www.contrarianconsulting.com/101-questions-for-any-sales-situation/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reprinted with permission&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-qualifying-the-prospect&#34;&gt;I. Qualifying the Prospect&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the process of determining whether the inquiry is appropriate for your business in terms of size, relevance, seriousness, and related factors. In other words, you don’t want to pursue a lead which can’t result in legitimate—and worthwhile—business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why do you think we might be a good match?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is there budget allocated for this project?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How important is this need (on a scale of 1-10)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is your timing to accomplish this?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who, if anyone, is demanding that this be accomplished?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How soon are you willing to begin?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you made a commitment to proceed, or are you still analyzing?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are your key decision criteria in choosing a resource?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you tried this before (will this be a continuing endeavor)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is your organization seeking formal proposals for this work?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Point: You want to determine whether the potential work is large enough for your involvement, relevant to your expertise, and near enough on the horizon to merit rapid responsiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ii-finding-the-economic-buyer&#34;&gt;II. Finding the Economic Buyer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic buyer is the person who can write a check in return for your value contribution. He or she is the ONLY buyer to be concerned about. Contrary to a great deal of poor advice, the economic buyer is virtually never in human resources, training, meeting planning, or related support areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whose budget will support this initiative?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who can immediately approve this project?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To whom will people look for support, approval, and credibility?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who controls the resources required to make this happen?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who has initiated this request?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who will claim responsibility for the results?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who will be seen as the main sponsor and/or champion?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you have to seek anyone else’s approval?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who will accept or reject proposals?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you and I were to shake hands, could I begin tomorrow?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Point: The larger the organization, the more the number of economic buyers. They need not be the CEO or owner, but must be able to authorize and produce payment. Committees are never economic buyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;iii-rebutting-objections&#34;&gt;III. Rebutting Objections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Obstacles are those terrible things you see when you take your eyes off the goal,” said philosopher Hannah More. Objections are a sign of interest. Turn them around to your benefit. Once you demolish objections, there is no longer a reason not to proceed in a partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions (in responding to an economic buyer’s objections)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why do you feel that way? (Get at the true cause.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we resolve this, can we then proceed? (Is this the sole objection?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;But isn’t that exactly why you need me? (The reversal approach.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What would satisfy you? (Make the buyer answer the objection.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What can we do to overcome that? (Demonstrate joint accountability.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is this unique? (Is there precedent for overcoming it?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What’s the consequence? (Is it really serious or merely an annoyance?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Isn’t that low probability? (Worry about likelihoods, not the remote.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shall I address that in the proposal? (Let’s focus on value.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why does it even matter in light of the results? (The ROI is the point.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Points: Don’t be on the defensive by trying to slay each objection with your sword, or you’ll eventually fall on it. Embrace the buyer in the “solutions,” and demonstrate that some objections are insignificant when compared with benefits (e.g., there will always be some unhappy employees in any change effort).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;iv-establishing-objectives&#34;&gt;IV. Establishing Objectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objectives are the outcomes which represent the client’s desired and improved conditions. They are never inputs (e.g., reports, focus groups, manuals) but rather always outputs (e.g., increased sales, reduced attrition, improved teamwork). Clear objectives prevent “scope creep” and enable a rational engagement and disengagement to take place, resulting in much greater consulting efficiency and profit margins. (Note that items IV, V, and VI—objectives, measures, and value—are the basis of conceptual agreement.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the ideal outcome you’d like to experience?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What results are you trying to accomplish?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What better product/service/customer condition are you seeking?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why are you seeking to do this (work/project/engagement)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How would the operation be different as a result of this work?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What would be the return on investment (sales, assets, equity, etc.)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How would image/repute/credibility be improved?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What harm (e.g., stress, dysfunction, turf wars, etc.) would be alleviated?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How much would you gain on the competition as a result?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How would your value proposition be improved?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Points: Most buyers know what they want but not necessarily what they need. By pushing the buyer on the end results you are helping to articulate and formalize the client’s perceived benefits, thereby increasing your own value in the process. Without clear objectives you do not have a legitimate project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;v-establishing-metrics&#34;&gt;V. Establishing Metrics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Metrics” are measures of progress toward the objectives, which enable you and the client to ascertain the rate and totality of success. They assign proper credit to you and your efforts, and also signify when the project is complete (objectives are met) and it is proper to disengage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How will you know we’ve accomplished your intent?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How, specifically, will the operation be different when we’re done?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How will you measure this?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What indicators will you use to assess our progress?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who or what will report on our results (against the objectives)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you already have measures in place you intend to apply?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the rate of return (on sales, investment, etc.) that you seek?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How will we know the public, employees, and/or customers perceive it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each time we talk, what standard will tell us we’re progressing?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How would you know it if you tripped over it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Points: Measures can be subjective, so long as you and the client agree on who is doing the measuring and how. For example, the buyer’s observation that he or she is called upon less to settle “turf” disputes and has fewer complaints from direct reports aimed at colleagues are valid measures for the objective of “improved teamwork.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;vi-assessing-value&#34;&gt;VI. Assessing Value&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Determining the value of the project for the client’s organization is the most critical aspect of conceptual agreement and pre-proposal interaction. That’s because when the buyer stipulates to significant value, the fee is placed in proper perspective (ROI) and is seldom an issue of contention. Conversations with the buyer should always focus on value and never on fee or price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What will these results mean for your organization?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How would you assess the actual return (ROI, ROA, ROS, ROE, etc.)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What would be the extent of the improvement (or correction)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How will these results impact the bottom line?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are the annualized savings (first year might be deceptive)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the intangible impact (e.g., on repute, safety, comfort, etc.)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How would you, personally, be better off or better supported?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the scope of the impact (on customers, employees, vendors)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How important is this compared to your overall responsibilities?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What if this fails?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Points: Subjective value (stress alleviated) can be every bit as important as more tangible results (higher sales). Never settle for “Don’t worry, it’s important.” Find out how important, because that will dictate the acceptable fee range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;vii-determining-the-budget-range&#34;&gt;VII. Determining the Budget Range&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too much guessing takes place in the absence of a general understanding about how much the prospect intends to invest (prior to understanding the full value proposition). In many cases, the budget is fixed and entirely inappropriate, and in others it represents a better understanding of the ROI than that of the consultant! (Don’t forget, this presupposes you’re talking to an economic buyer.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you arrived at a budget or investment range for this project?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are funds allocated, or must they be requested?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is your expectation of investment required?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;So we don’t waste time, are there parameters to remain within?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you done this before, and at what investment level?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are you able to authorize during this fiscal year?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can I assume that a strong proposition will justify proper expenditure?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How much are you prepared to invest to gain these dramatic results?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a dramatic return, will you consider a larger investment?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s be frank: What are you willing to spend?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Points: There is nothing wrong with exceeding the budget expectation if you muster a strong enough value proposition. But don’t even proceed with a proposal if the prospect has a seriously misguided expectation of the investment need, or simply has an inadequate, fixed budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;viii-preventing-unforeseen-obstacles&#34;&gt;VIII. Preventing Unforeseen Obstacles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As comedienne Gilda Radnor used to say, “It’s always something.” Inevitably, it seems, the best laid plains are undermined by objections, occurrences, and serendipity from left field. Fortunately, there are questions to establish some preventive actions against even the unforeseen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is there anything we haven’t discussed which could get in the way?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the past, what has occurred to derail potential projects like this?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What haven’t I asked you that I should have about the environment?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What do you estimate the probability is of our going forward?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are you surprised by anything I’ve said or that we’ve agreed upon?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this point, are you still going to make this decision yourself?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What, if anything, do you additionally need to hear from me?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is anything likely to change in the organization in the near future?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are you awaiting the results of any other initiatives or decisions?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I get this proposal to you tomorrow, how soon will you decide?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Points: Make sure that your project isn’t contingent upon other events transpiring (or not transpiring). If the buyer is holding out on you, these questions will make it more difficult to dissemble. Build into your proposal benefits to outweigh the effects of any external factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ix-increasing-the-size-of-the-sale&#34;&gt;IX. Increasing the Size of the Sale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once conceptual agreement is gained, it makes sense to capitalize on the common ground and strive for the largest possible relationship. Most consultants don’t obtain larger contracts because they don’t ask for or suggest them. You can’t possibly lose anything attempting to increase the business at this juncture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would you be amenable to my providing a variety of options?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is this the only place (division, department, geography) applicable?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would it be wise to extend this through implementation and oversight?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Should we plan to also coach key individuals essential to the project?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would you benefit from benchmarking against other firms?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would you also like an idea of what a retainer might look like?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are there others in your position with like needs I should see?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do your subordinates possess the skills to support you appropriately?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Should we run focus groups/other sampling to test employee reactions?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would you like me to test customer response at various stages?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Points: If you don’t ask, you don’t get. Don’t throw everything including the kitchen sink into your proposal in an attempt to justify your fee. Instead, “unbundle” what you’re capable of providing and add them back in at additional fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;x-going-for-the-close&#34;&gt;X. Going for the Close&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home stretch, but not across the finish line. Runners who slow up at the approaching tape lose to someone else with a better late “kick.” Run through the tape at full speed by driving the conversation right through the close of the sale and the check clearing the bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the proposal reflects our last discussions, how soon can we begin?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is it better to start immediately, or wait for the first of the month?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is there anything at all preventing our working together at this point?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How rapidly are you prepared to begin once you see the proposal?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you get the proposal tomorrow, can I call Friday at 10 for approval?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;While I’m here, should I begin some of the preliminary work today?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would you like to shake hands and get started, proposal to follow?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you prefer a corporate check or to wire the funds electronically?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;May I allocate two days early next week to start my interviews?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can we proceed?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Points: There is never a better time than when you’re in front of the buyer and he or she is in agreement and excited about the project. Even without a proposal, beginning immediately “pours cement” on the conceptual agreement and greatly diminishes the possibility of being derailed by surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;xi-the-most-vital-question&#34;&gt;XI. The Most Vital Question&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the preceding 100 questions are actually based on the reaction to one question which we often fail to ask of the most difficult person of all. And unlike most of the prior inquiries, it’s a simple binary question, with a clear “yes or no” response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Question&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you believe it yourself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key Points: The first sale is always to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© Alan Weiss 2009. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Determining Value-Based Fees for Software Projects</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/determining-value-based-fees-for-software-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2009 18:47:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/determining-value-based-fees-for-software-projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.davidwinch.co.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;David Winch&lt;/a&gt; noticed me talking on Twitter about &amp;#8220;Determining Value-Based Fees for Software Projects&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically I said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;While I generally agree that Value-Based Fees (&lt;em&gt;a la&lt;/em&gt; Alan Weiss) are the best way to charge and get what you&amp;#8217;re worth as a consultant, I don&amp;#8217;t know how well this approach translates to the software development domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;How do you determine value to the client without spending inordinate time performing requirements discovery and analysis? How do you manage change requests in a Value-Based fees approach?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This apparently piqued David&amp;#8217;s interest, so he posted a reply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Software development is one of the key areas to be adopting a Value-Based Pricing approach &amp;#8211; as you indicate following the Alan Weiss/Ron Baker &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;I think you&amp;#8217;ve almost answered your own question here. You DO need to discover a lot of information before you can suggest a Value Based fee but not, I would argue, specifically to do with requirements, and not in a time consuming manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;There are efficient ways of finding out as much as possible about the client&amp;#8217;s PROBLEM and the circumstances surrounding it. Then you can go through the remaining stages of the &amp;#8216;Sales Conversation&amp;#8217; and present your options (see A Weiss) and then the associated fees &amp;#8211; all in the space of say an hour or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;m guessing that your &amp;#8216;value (to the client &amp;#8211; not the price tag) package&amp;#8217; options might all start with a research project to work with the client to discover and agree the detailed requirements of a software solution to the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Having agreed (in writing) with the client the scope of the &amp;#8216;value package&amp;#8217; they have selected and your FIXED fee, any &amp;#8216;Change Requests&amp;#8217; can be simply dealt with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;If it&amp;#8217;s within the scope of the project, it gets done for no additional fee! If it isn&amp;#8217;t, then this is a separate chargeable project! You will be asking the client if they would like you to stop work on the current project while you complete the new one, or whether they&amp;#8217;d like you to finish the current one first. As Jonathan Stark (another Value Based Pricing disciple, from the software world) points out, you can only run one project with any one client at any one time!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This elicited further questions from me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Using the Value-Based approach, how does one deal with the &amp;#8220;we&amp;#8217;re a startup, we can&amp;#8217;t afford that!&amp;#8221; response to a proposal? Often I am asked to design/develop websites for clients, which in my opinion is pretty much commoditized at this point. While the value to the client could be extraordinary, the fact that there is limited price elasticity here is working against me. How do I value-price something that can be had at similar quality for a fraction of the cost?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once more David replied:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;d question &amp;#8216;similar quality&amp;#8217;! You are unique! Only you can deliver your project! I work with a web design colleague and we recently talked to a one-man-band about his first website. We didn&amp;#8217;t ask his budget but I&amp;#8217;d guess a few hundred pounds. After the full &amp;#8216;Value Conversation&amp;#8217; based &amp;#8216;Sales Conversation&amp;#8217; (which took us about 1½ hours) he agreed to a £4,000 fixed fee for an e-commerce site. Having seen what it would mean to him to have a website that sells, he found a way of getting the money to invest in the enormous return, and paid 50% up front a fortnight later!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I responded with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;How did you convince him to cough up the equivalent of US$8,000 when he could have easily gone with any number of hosted solutions for under $100/month? I suspect the value conversation took 15 minutes and the sales conversation took the rest?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David&amp;#8217;s response was to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;The Value Conversation is one of four &amp;#8216;Conversations&amp;#8217; that make up the Sales Conversation, and mostly takes longest of the four. The skill is in helping the client understand for themselves the value of having the problem fixed. In this case we&amp;#8217;ll help him achieve increased gross profits of over £100,000 per year with the new site . There will be additional (chargeable) work involved in driving sufficient traffic to the site, but even so he&amp;#8217;s backing a winner at odds of better than 10 to 1!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/2009/08/09/determining-value-based-fees-for-software-projects-part-2/&#34;&gt;Read Part 2 here&lt;/a&gt;_&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>