<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>General on Mark Richman Consulting</title>
    <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/general/</link>
    <description>Recent content in General on Mark Richman Consulting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 01:31:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/general/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>When You Need a Technology Advisor</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/when-you-need-a-technology-advisor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 01:31:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/when-you-need-a-technology-advisor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re an established business looking to raise the bar, or a startup delivering new technology to market, you need expert knowledge and experience to advise you. In this article, I’m going to discuss what a technology advisor does, and how you’ll be far better off working with one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who works with a technology advisor?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business owners and technology executives&lt;/strong&gt; need to make quick but informed decisions. Top line revenue growth, and bottom line profit are key drivers. A technology advisor can bring their considerable expertise to bear in supplementing understanding, finding value, and accelerating learning. These business leaders can take advantage of proven approaches to common challenges, and discover value in new ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investors&lt;/strong&gt; often call upon a technology advisor when evaluating a new opportunity. These engagements are called technical due diligence. If an investor is going to spend millions to acquire a startup, or take one public, it must be certain of the content it’s buying, and how quickly it can monetize the investment.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Startup founders&lt;/strong&gt;, unlike traditional business owners and investors, have a vision, but often lack the expertise to realize it. A technology advisor can help guide and launch a new venture through both strategic and tactical expertise.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you need a technology advisor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;A technology advisor can help accelerate business growth by applying the following expertise:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Develop business plans, focusing on cost and time estimates for delivering a solution&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Create prototypes to help communicate ideas to investors and business partners&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Help select the appropriate technologies and vendors to realize business goals&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Guide the software development process, ensuring repeatable delivery of high-quality products and features&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Evaluate staffing needs and help source, interview, and select candidates at all levels of the organization&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Improve individual and team performance through training and coaching&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How you’re better off when I’m gone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;One of the best reasons why startups call me for advice is the tremendous value I provide &lt;strong&gt;without diluting the firm’s equity&lt;/strong&gt;. Many early stage startup founders don’t want a full time CIO or CTO, and will call upon me tactically while preserving the value of their shares.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;I also work with established firms to help select technology delivery partners, both onshore and offshore. I provide an objective assessment of the capabilities and quality of vendors. Entrusting a third party to help grow a business is daunting. Imagine the &lt;strong&gt;cost of making a mistake&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;For individuals, I help accelerate learning and and improve life balance. New ways of thinking, tools, techniques, and processes produce &lt;strong&gt;dramatic results&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All Rights Reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Management Ignores the Process</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/when-management-ignores-the-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2015 14:52:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/when-management-ignores-the-process/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I was recently working with a consulting client who was suffering from a productivity decline in her organization over the past year. My client, a VP of a software development organization, recently adopted Scrum as its Agile software development process. When I conducted interviews with key team members, a common complaint emerged: “Management is always ignoring the process!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most organizations follow some form of process, regardless of the domain. These processes range from lightweight (almost nonexistent) to the draconian. The amount of process varies wildly based on number of employees, clarity of roles and responsibilities, compliance requirements, degree of risk tolerance, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting is that management are usually the ones beating the “follow the process” drum, not the staff. My client was different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-agile-is-different&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Agile is different&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since adopting Scrum and Agile practices, my client’s team has come to rely on the safety net the process offers over traditional methodologies. Controlled iterative development, empiricism, and autonomy have all contributed to higher quality software at a faster pace, with dramatically reduced defects. &lt;strong&gt;And then suddenly, this all started falling apart.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new CEO joined the organization, and with him came new priorities, new customers, and a focus on new revenue. Management, strangely less empowered than the teams they manage, followed the leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high velocity, high quality performance the team had been enjoying was disrupted by some unwelcome old symptoms from management. See if any of these situations resonate with you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;out-of-band-high-priority-requests&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out-of-band high-priority requests&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One team member explained to me that their planned work (two weeks’ worth) had been hijacked to accommodate an executive’s pet project, with no explanation as to &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; this work was important to the organization. Management followed orders and pushed this work down the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-everything-is-a-priority-then-nothing-is-a-priority&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When everything is a priority, then nothing is a priority&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scrum, the process adopted by my client’s team, employs a prioritized Product Backlog to plan upcoming work, and a Sprint Backlog to plan work in progress. The goal is to constantly deliver maximum value to the organization, while maintaining quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One manager began to nitpick certain subjective “spit and polish” issues, demanding the team to correct these while other &lt;strong&gt;prioritized&lt;/strong&gt; work was already underway. If the process were followed, these changes would be welcomed by the team, and given the attention they deserved. Instead, the team was distracted by the curveball, and failed to complete a key feature on time due to the distraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;priority-via-intimidation&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Priority via intimidation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While sometimes overt, intimidation by management can often be subtle. Managers who try to act as part of the team, often effectively, sometimes leverage their position in the org chart to influence priorities. One team member, a Product Owner, shared with me that her manager, while acting as part of the team in most instances, sometimes reverted to subtle “bullying” to get a feature prioritized. The problem here is that the Product Owner directly reported to the manager, a clear indication that the organizational relationships didn’t support the level of empowerment and autonomy needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lack-of-mission-or-purpose&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of mission or purpose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teams need a purpose in order to deliver effectively. Simply being told to “make widget X run faster” often isn’t sufficient to engage teams in a solution. Team members might ask “why I am working on this?” A better approach would be to frame the feature request in context: “We are losing $250,000 per year in productivity because widget X is slow.” Here, we can align the organizational objective with the technical solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-can-help&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How I can help&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked with my client to bring these issues to light, much to her shock and dismay. We agreed that the organizational structure was not conducive to Agile software development. We instituted a number of changes to get back on track. First, the role of “manager” in the context of product development was deprecated. Instead, the Product Owner was empowered to make feature priority decisions, and in cases where conflict occurred with a manager, the Scrum Master served as arbiter. Next, the Scrum Master role was charged with the “check and balance” of ensuring that the Product Owner groomed only those Product Backlog items whose value was clear. I also encouraged skip-level meetings between my client (the VP) and individual team members, which can be used as a tool to bring to light any concerns the team might have, but have been previously uncomfortable raising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been about six weeks since we made these changes. The realignment has been energizing to the team, as evidenced by unsolicited feedback from my client. While sliding back into old habits often happens, overall team productivity and morale are dramatically improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How is your process helping you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© Mark Richman 2015&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools of the Trade</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/tools-of-the-trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2009 13:10:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/tools-of-the-trade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://afreshcup.com/2009/10/14/double-shot-561/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;colleagues&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a title=&#34;Ruby on Rails&#34; href=&#34;http://www.rubyonrails.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt; community have been posting a “tools of the trade” blog post, covering their hardware and software preferences. Now that I am nearly Microsoft-free, I figured I&amp;#8217;d update my list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hardware&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/macpro/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Apple Mac Pro&lt;/a&gt; 8-core Xeon, 10GB RAM, 320GB + 500GB 7200rpm SATA drives. This is my main box and the best computer I&amp;#8217;ve ever owned. I use the 500GB drive as my Time Machine backup drive, but I am looking into other backup options as Time Machine is slow and there are anecdotal reliability issues, but now that I&amp;#8217;m running Snow Leopard, I haven&amp;#8217;t experienced any (not that I&amp;#8217;ve attempted a restore yet either). I&amp;#8217;m going to look into SuperDuper!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dual Dell FP1905 19&amp;#8243; LCD monitors. I hate them. The colors don&amp;#8217;t match, no matter how I calibrate them, and they are too small for the type of work I do now. They also suffer from burn-in and ghosting. I&amp;#8217;m considering a new &lt;a href=&#34;http://accessories.us.dell.com/sna/products/Monitors/productdetail.aspx?c=us&amp;l=en&amp;s=dhs&amp;cs=19&amp;sku=223-4890&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dell UltraSharp 3008WFP 30-inch&lt;/a&gt;, unless Apple announces something better for less money (ain&amp;#8217;t gonna happen).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;External WD USB/FireWire hard drive for additional backups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.m-audio.com/products/en_us/FastTrackPro.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;M-Audio Fast Track Pro&lt;/a&gt; audio interface. I play guitar, and use this to record via the Shure SM-57 mic in front of my amps (not that this has anything to do with my work, but it&amp;#8217;s cool nonetheless). My music gear is the subject for another blog entry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/iphone/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Apple iPhone 3G&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/macosx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mac OS X 10.6 Snow Leopard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/macosx/refinements/enhancements-refinements.html#mail&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mail.app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_Terminal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Terminal.app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vienna-rss.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Vienna&lt;/a&gt; RSS Reader&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/firefox/personal.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://macromates.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TextMate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://culturedcode.com/things/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vmware.com/products/fusion/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;VMware Fusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openoffice.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;OpenOffice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://adium.im/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Adium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://colloquy.info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Colloquy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/itunes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tweetdeck.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TweetDeck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skype.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Skype&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ksuther.com/chax/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Chax&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.postgresql.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PostgreSQL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rubyonrails.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sqlpower.ca/page/architect&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Power*Architect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hosting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linode.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Linode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.godaddy.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GoDaddy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I’m a WS-I Advocate!</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/im-a-ws-i-advocate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2007 06:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/im-a-ws-i-advocate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am proud to be an Advocate of the Web Services Interoperability Organization (WS-I). WS-I is an open industry consortium chartered to facilitate Web services interoperability and to accelerate Web services adoption in the marketplace. For more information: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ws-i.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ws-i.org&#34;&gt;http://www.ws-i.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&#34;width: 394px; height: 192px&#34; src=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/WS-I_Advocate_Color_sm.gif&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;WS-I Advocate&#34; title=&#34;WS-I Advocate&#34; width=&#34;394&#34; height=&#34;192&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What tools do you use?</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/what-tools-do-you-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2007 22:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/what-tools-do-you-use/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I get this question a lot. The short answer, of course, is &amp;ldquo;it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;depends&amp;rdquo;. That is, I&amp;rsquo;m a right-tool-for-the-right-job kinda guy. However, since&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I make my living in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.microsoft.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Microsoft&#34;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/a&gt; ecosystem, I&amp;rsquo;m naturally biased. Generally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;speaking, I use mostly open source tools, unless there is a compelling reason&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to use a commercial one. Here&amp;rsquo;s my list (subject to frequent change, of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;course):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;microsoft-visual-studio&#34;&gt;Microsoft Visual Studio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/vstudio/default.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Visual Studio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt; is the &lt;strong&gt;best&lt;/strong&gt; IDE hands down. Yeah, I&amp;rsquo;ve&lt;br /&gt; tried notepad and cmd.exe, but it&amp;rsquo;s just not the same. If you&amp;rsquo;re poor (or&lt;br /&gt; cheap), the FREE &lt;a href=&#34;http://msdn.microsoft.com/vstudio/express/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Express Editions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt; are pretty good too. My language preference is &lt;a href=&#34;http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/vcsharp/aa336809.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;C#&lt;/a&gt;. I was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://java.sun.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Java&lt;/a&gt; guy for a long time, so this was just a&lt;br /&gt; natural progression for me. No &lt;a href=&#34;http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/vbasic/default.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;VB&lt;/a&gt;, please.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;jetbrains-resharper&#34;&gt;JetBrains ReSharper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jetbrains.com/resharper/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ReSharper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt; is a &lt;strong&gt;phenomenal&lt;/strong&gt; productivity add-in&lt;br /&gt; for Visual Studio. &amp;ldquo;Version 3.0 brings unrivalled code analysis, a superior&lt;br /&gt; unit testing solution, Go to Symbol navigation, a handy To-do Explorer with&lt;br /&gt; multiple unit test sessions, and many other features &amp;#8211; to boost individual and&lt;br /&gt; team productivity in the world of .NET development&amp;rdquo;. &lt;span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;No, it&amp;rsquo;s not free, but it&amp;rsquo;s well worth the&lt;br /&gt; small price tag.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;subversion&#34;&gt;Subversion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  For years I suffered with &lt;a href=&#34;http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/vstudio/aa718670.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Visual SourceSafe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s junk, and just plain dangerous. Don&amp;rsquo;t use it. Ever! &lt;a href=&#34;http://subversion.tigris.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Subversion&lt;/a&gt; is my tool of choice for my&lt;br /&gt; personal projects, and my recommendation to clients who can&amp;rsquo;t afford &lt;a href=&#34;http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/teamsystem/aa718934.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Visual Studio Team&lt;br /&gt; Foundation Server&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s price tag.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tortoisesvn&#34;&gt;TortoiseSVN&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  If you use Windows and Subversion, then you need &lt;a href=&#34;http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TortoiseSVN&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;aqua-data-studio&#34;&gt;Aqua Data Studio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aquafold.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Aqua Data Studio&lt;/a&gt; is a&lt;br /&gt; commercial tool that I use on occasion to script data out of large tables,&lt;br /&gt; since I&amp;rsquo;m a dummy and can&amp;rsquo;t figure out how to get SQL Server Management Studio&lt;br /&gt; to spit out INSERT statements for all my data. It also works with just about&lt;br /&gt; every DBMS there is, just in case you&amp;rsquo;re thrown onto a MySQL or Oracle project&amp;hellip;gasp!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ghostdoc&#34;&gt;GhostDoc&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roland-weigelt.de/ghostdoc/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.roland-weigelt.de/ghostdoc/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reflector&#34;&gt;Reflector&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aisto.com/roeder/dotnet/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.aisto.com/roeder/dotnet/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;web-service-software-factory&#34;&gt;Web Service Software Factory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codeplex.com/servicefactory&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.codeplex.com/servicefactory&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;subsonic&#34;&gt;SubSonic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://subsonicproject.com/default.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://subsonicproject.com/default.aspx&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;log4net&#34;&gt;Log4net&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://logging.apache.org/log4net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://logging.apache.org/log4net/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;urlrewriter-net&#34;&gt;URLRewriter.NET&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://urlrewriter.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://urlrewriter.net/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;textpad&#34;&gt;TextPad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://textpad.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://textpad.com/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;strike&#34;&gt;&lt;strike&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaim&lt;/strike&gt; Pidgin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://pidgin.im/pidgin/home/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://pidgin.im/pidgin/home/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nunit&#34;&gt;NUnit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nunit.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.nunit.org/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cruisecontrol-net&#34;&gt;CruiseControl.NET&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://confluence.public.thoughtworks.org/display/CCNET&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://confluence.public.thoughtworks.org/display/CCNET&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fxcop&#34;&gt;FxCop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gotdotnet.com/team/fxcop/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.gotdotnet.com/team/fxcop/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tail-for-win32&#34;&gt;Tail for Win32&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://tailforwin32.sourceforge.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://tailforwin32.sourceforge.net/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;MsoNormal&#34;&gt;
  I&#39;m sure there are more that I can&#39;t think of off the top of my head, so I&#39;ll keep this list up to date as I discover some new and cool tools.&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Now using BlogEngine.NET!</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/now-using-blogenginenet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2007 07:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/now-using-blogenginenet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.dotnetblogengine.net/themes/blogenginehome/images/benlogo80.gif&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;BlogEngine.NET Logo&#34; title=&#34;BlogEngine.NET Logo&#34; width=&#34;266&#34; height=&#34;80&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dotnetblogengine.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hilite&#34;&gt;BlogEngine&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&#34;hilite&#34;&gt;NET&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is an open source .&lt;span class=&#34;hilite&#34;&gt;NET&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;blogging project that was born out of desire for a better blog&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;platform. A blog platform with less complexity, easy customization, and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;one that takes advantage of the latest .&lt;span class=&#34;hilite&#34;&gt;NET&lt;/span&gt; features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hilite&#34;&gt;BlogEngine&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&#34;hilite&#34;&gt;NET&lt;/span&gt; was designed using the current .&lt;span class=&#34;hilite&#34;&gt;NET&lt;/span&gt; framework and focused on simplicity, ease of extendibility, and innovative features. With &lt;span class=&#34;hilite&#34;&gt;BlogEngine&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&#34;hilite&#34;&gt;NET&lt;/span&gt;, we hope to create the natural blog of choice for all .&lt;span class=&#34;hilite&#34;&gt;NET&lt;/span&gt; developers world wide.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>