<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Analytics on Mark Richman Consulting</title>
    <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/analytics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Analytics on Mark Richman Consulting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 14:20:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/analytics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>What’s your SCAM Strategy for 2016?</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/whats-your-scam-strategy-for-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 14:20:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/whats-your-scam-strategy-for-2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;wp-image-776 alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM.png&#34; alt=&#34;SCAM&#34; width=&#34;328&#34; height=&#34;314&#34; srcset=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM-52x50.png 52w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM-300x287.png 300w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM.png 790w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 328px) 100vw, 328px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’re in Q4, your technology strategy for 2016 should be well formed. So what’s your plan for SCAM? The Social, Cloud, Analytics, and Mobile (SCAM) stack presents a framework in which organizations can align marketing and technical efforts with a customer-centric strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;social-media-is-the-new-crm&#34;&gt;Social Media is the New CRM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have an innate need for affiliation. We join clubs, professional associations, play sports, and even practice our religions, to one degree or another, in order to satisfy this need. Social media is the modern extension of this community-building. We friend, tweet, pin, share, and like; we are not only expressing our individuality online, but also identifying with groups and brands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s all well and good for sharing cat videos and pictures of your kids, right? &lt;strong&gt;WRONG&lt;/strong&gt;. Social media is a powerful tool to engage your existing customers, and attract new ones, all by capitalizing on their need for affiliation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.noahfleming.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Noah Fleming&lt;/a&gt; writes about community in his book &lt;em&gt;Evergreen&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;#8220;as our customers are becoming more interconnected, they are naturally beginning to build elements of community on their own. Furthermore, if you don&amp;#8217;t create a strong customer community, you can be guaranteed that your competitors will.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional Customer Relationship Management (CRM) systems are transactional in nature. They collect data on customers, transactions, and contact histories. &lt;strong&gt;Social CRM&lt;/strong&gt; allows companies to directly interact with customers &lt;em&gt;en masse&lt;/em&gt;, observe how they communicate with each other, and gauge sentiment about your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media isn&amp;#8217;t just for marketers either. Inbound customer service also leverages social media, offering customers a deeper sense of connectedness than an 800 number or a contact form on your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my clients is the CEO/Owner of an online vitamin supplement company. We were discussing how his larger competitors engaged with customers using social media. While these companies had a team of customer service folks monitoring social media, and interacting with customers, they were too big for their CEO to respond personally. I suggested this was an opportunity for him to &lt;strong&gt;differentiate&lt;/strong&gt; by being directly accessible by his customers via social media. He quickly discovered that he could more quickly obtain customer information than waiting passively for new sales to come in. Learning his customers’ demographics through social media analytics (more on that later) allowed him to save money on advertising campaigns that targeted the wrong segments. Talking with me on Twitter as &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mrichman&#34;&gt;@mrichman&lt;/a&gt; instead of promoting at me with an ad goes a long way to building trust and loyalty through transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cloud&#34;&gt;Cloud&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All organizations are under increasing pressure to maximize their return on technology investment. As budgets shift funds from IT to marketing, the IT organization seeks to save costs. Leveraging a cloud provider, as opposed to maintaining on-premise infrastructure, takes advantage of economies of scale to consume more computing power at lower costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving to the cloud allows for investment using operational expenditures (OPEX), rather than capital expenditures (CAPEX). CFOs no longer concern themselves with depreciating assets, and large lump-sum investments in infrastructure. This approach &lt;strong&gt;frees cash&lt;/strong&gt; for investment in other areas of the business, and reduces the footprint of the IT department as a cost center in the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of my clients are e-commerce companies, and often have to prepare their infrastructure for peaks in traffic. They usually do this by purchasing far more equipment than is needed for typical demand, and often hosting in redundant data centers to mitigate the risk of downtime. Cloud environments allow for &lt;strong&gt;flexible computing power &lt;/strong&gt;that scales on-demand, paying for only what is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security concerns, maintenance, and upgrades account for significant investment in both service agreements and labor. Many cloud infrastructures eliminate or greatly reduce the constant demand for mundane maintenance tasks. Cloud providers with more specialized staff and a greater focus on security can offer CIOs peace of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite reason to move to the cloud is &lt;strong&gt;speed&lt;/strong&gt;. What used to take weeks or even months to spec out, order, provision, and configure, and can now be done in hours or less. This allows organizations to rapidly respond to changes in market demand, and the organization can better avoid the losing proposition of an on-premise physical infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;analytics&#34;&gt;Analytics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, “big data” is all the rage. But all the data in the world is useless if it’s not relevant and actionable. That’s where analytics come in. Your data can come from a wide variety of sources, from social media, e-commerce transactions, website traffic, financial reports, and so on. We’re able to do more than just track clicks now. We can infer relationships between customers and our products and services, and make predictions about their behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working with a number of clients to develop 1:1 marketing programs (also called “one-off” marketing) using historical transaction data. Using analytics tools (often more than one), I look at repeat vs. non-repeat customers, time of day or week, and geographic location in order to segment the customer base. Using this data, we can tailor email campaigns, intercept promotions, and product recommendations to a specific customer’s shopping preferences. Ultimately, this not only increases conversion rates, but also average order value and purchase frequency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mobile&#34;&gt;Mobile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your web strategy is not mobile-first, you&amp;#8217;re doing it wrong. Over half of all web searches are now from mobile devices. Optimizing your website for mobility or having a native application can take advantage of your customers&amp;#8217; location and identity, for example, allowing for a more customized experience. Providing mobile-optimized productivity applications to your workforce will also enable them to be more productive. Many users now have three or more mobile devices &amp;#8211; smartphones, tablets, laptops, and even watches. It&amp;#8217;s more important than ever to target these devices as first-class citizens as part of your technology strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;challenge-questions-for-leaders&#34;&gt;Challenge Questions for Leaders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In what ways does your social media and social CRM strategy engage more prospects and customers, and build a community?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is your enterprise architecture equipped to support SCAM challenges?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can your software development process keep up with the rapidly evolving SCAM landscape?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does your team have the tools, skills, and processes in place to execute your SCAM strategy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CIO should become the CDO</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/the-cio-should-become-the-cdo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 16:33:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/the-cio-should-become-the-cdo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div&gt;
  The role of CIO as Chief &lt;em&gt;Infrastructure&lt;/em&gt; Officer is becoming increasingly irrelevant. IT budgets have shifted to Marketing. Corporate infrastructure is moving to the cloud. So what&amp;#8217;s left? &lt;strong&gt;Data&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-the-chief-data-officer&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enter the Chief Data Officer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Data belongs to the business, not just to IT. The CDO represents these business interests. If the CIO&amp;#8217;s job is simply to keep the lights on, that&amp;#8217;s not something the rest of the business will relate to. If CIOs are to survive, they must evolve, much like the technology for which they have been responsible.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Business intelligence, data analytics, and the value delivered to the business from SCAM (social, cloud, analytics, mobile) will become the primary driver of strategy. We already see this transformation occurring, and CMOs continue to wrestle away not only dollars, but also organizational ownership of the customer. The CMO becomes the CDO&amp;#8217;s best customer.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-cdo-is-a-hybrid-executive&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The CDO is a Hybrid Executive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The most effective CDO will be a &lt;i&gt;hybrid&lt;/i&gt; executive. Often graduating from a CIO or CTO role, their responsibilities will overlap several disciplines:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decision Management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Digital Transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The CDO is a transformational leader, driving business value by integrating emerging technologies with external marketing and customer facing initiatives with internal processes and applications.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-the-cio-can-thrive&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How the CIO can Thrive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The successful CIO will be the one who can take their organization and gear it toward the ability to program infrastructure as code, and serve new application development, driven by social, cloud, analytics, and mobile.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;challenge-questions-for-leaders&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge Questions for Leaders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What opportunities do you have for creating and enhancing the business value of data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your strategy for responding to SCAM (social, cloud, analytics, mobile) requirements of the business?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will you reshape the business to take advantage of data and technology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All Rights Reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Realtime Voice of the Customer</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/realtime-voice-of-the-customer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 16:04:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/realtime-voice-of-the-customer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been working with my best clients on integrating realtime Voice of the Customer (VoC) technologies into their e-commerce operations. The results have been enlightening and profitable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started with e-commerce systems around 2003, the industry was still in its infancy, and many customers still followed up online orders with multiple confirmation phone calls, or would use a vendor&amp;#8217;s website to get their phone number to place an order. This seems archaic now, just a few years later, when almost nobody picks up the phone to make a purchase. As e-commerce presences grew, the dual phone/web channels could not scale, so the direct and real time feedback of the customer was often lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we capture the Voice of the Customer, gather comments, and learn about opportunities for improvement if we don&amp;#8217;t speak to them anymore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E-commerce vendors developed email-based surveys to fill the gap left by waning telephone sales. These surveys are sent anywhere from the time of order confirmation to several days after delivery. The customer would complete the survey at their leisure, or not at all. Much of the shopping experience itself is usually out of mind by the time an email survey is completed. Over time, these have become little more than noise in a customer&amp;#8217;s inbox, and not very actionable by vendors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not particularly useful to capture the &lt;strong&gt;shopping experience&lt;/strong&gt; itself, email surveys are still effective in a couple of cases. Major vendors, Amazon included, use email surveys to solicit feedback on the products themselves, packaging quality, or shipping speed. Most customers, however, never fill these out unless there is something negative to report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we capture the essence of the customer&amp;#8217;s shopping experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exit Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more immediate feedback, exit surveys are usually placed on the order confirmation page, or when navigating away from this page. Customers&amp;#8217; shopping experience is still fresh in their mind, and both kudos and frustrations are more readily captured. This can also serve as an effective diagnostic tool for any technical problems with a website. I worked with one client, a $400M online retailer, to implement on-page exit surveys, and the results were astounding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their support number would occasionally ring with a customer complaint of checkout issues, only to have the order completed over the phone. This event would never get escalated to the web team for investigation. Over time, these problems just festered until a major promotion went out, when the phone rang nonstop due to shopping cart glitches. The exit survey was directed to the web team, not customer service, and issues were triaged in realtime. The root cause of the website issues was corrected, and &lt;strong&gt;conversion rate improved dramatically&lt;/strong&gt; in a week. No more hours wasted scratching your head over funnel abandon rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realtime Chat&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web-based realtime chat is a terrific innovation for customers to speak to a live person, and comfortably ask questions and give feedback where a phone call is inconvenient or time consuming. Some customers are shy, or have language issues, and typing is just easier for them. Unless you&amp;#8217;re particularly short staffed, this is a fantastic tool, and there&amp;#8217;s no downside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intercept Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I absolutely LOVE these. I use them on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my own website&lt;/a&gt;. Unlike email or exit surveys, you can get realtime feedback from visitors who &lt;strong&gt;chose not to buy&lt;/strong&gt;. These surveys typically take the form of a popup, and ask just a couple of key questions about the shopping experience. I also set them up to capture email addresses for lead generation. I&amp;#8217;ve also set them up to capture Net Promoter Score (NPS), demographic information, or to leak promotion codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often hear concerns about the intrusive nature of these popups, and whether or not they increase bounce rates. Better tools are typically more passive and configurable, appearing only at the most opportune time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we love hearing from customers who spent money, we also need to hear from those who don&amp;#8217;t. You&amp;#8217;re not going to get these insights any other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you hear your customers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictive Analytics for E-Commerce</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/predictive-analytics-e-commerce/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2014 14:00:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/predictive-analytics-e-commerce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re like most online retailers, you face these common challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Competition in similar verticals
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      High marketing budgets
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      High cost of customer acquisition
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      High Customer attrition
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Low profit margins
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Assess your situation by answering the following questions:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      How do I lower my cost of acquisition?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Which factors can drive my customers towards repeat purchase?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      How can I increase the effectiveness of marketing campaigns?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Which assortment sales can improve my margins?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      How can I increase average order value (AOV)?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      How do I personalize my campaigns for maximum response?
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  There are many types of data available to you to address these challenges. In order to effectively target your marketing campaigns, you must effectively collect, analyze, and apply these data. Here are some potential data sources that you can leverage:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Social Media Streams
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Referring Websites
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Customer Transactions
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Web Logs
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Clickstream Data
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Customer Demographics
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Customer Service Logs
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are you currently aggregating these disparate data sources in order to optimize for sales? It is not enough to simply ask the data “what happened?” or even “why did it happen?” The most value can be derived from asking “what &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; happen?” (prediction) and then &lt;strong&gt;making it happen&lt;/strong&gt; (prescription). This approach will move your focus from hindsight to foresight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a predictive model, you will have increased confidence as to when customers will abandon a transaction, accept product recommendations, enroll in a continuity program, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prescriptive models, based on continued observations of predictive data, will allow you to tune your campaigns for maximum conversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staples, for example, executes over 1,500 multichannel campaigns annually based on over 25 million customer records. Jim Foreman, Director of Circulation and Analytics at Staples, reports &amp;#8220;We did a financial analysis of the implementation, and we found that we were getting an internal rate of return of 137%”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How would you like an ROI like that?!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the phases of the analytics life cycle, and some example models I can help you use to make better decisions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Customer Acquisition
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Acquisition Response Models
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Customer Value Scoring Models
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Customer Profiling &amp; Segmentation
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Campaign Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Customer Management
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Profitability Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Channel Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Call center analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Market Mix Modeling
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Relationship Expansion
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Loyalty (attrition) analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Cross-sell/Upsell Modeling
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Campaign Effectiveness
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Product Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Propensity Modeling
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Customer Retention
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Personalization
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Product Affinity
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Satisfaction &amp; Loyalty Indices
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Lifetime Value (LTV) Prediction
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Voice of the Customer Analytics
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Survey Analytics
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Social Media Analytics
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Sentiment Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Promoter/Detractor Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Text Analytics
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  How can you get from descriptive to &lt;i&gt;predictive&lt;/i&gt; analytics, and take your campaigns to the next level?
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>