<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>E Commerce on Mark Richman Consulting</title>
    <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/e-commerce/</link>
    <description>Recent content in E Commerce on Mark Richman Consulting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 20:31:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/e-commerce/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Must-Answer Tech Strategy Questions</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/five-must-answer-tech-strategy-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 20:31:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/five-must-answer-tech-strategy-questions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;​Many of my senior-executive clients have been called upon by their boards to get directly involved in technology issues. These boards are also starting to think strategically about technology, and how industry trends are shaping their companies&amp;#8217; future. More than ever, we need to ask questions that keep us focused on the right issues. While working with clients on new projects, or meeting prospective clients for the first time, I&amp;#8217;ve collected a series of &amp;#8220;must-answer&amp;#8221; questions that bring clarity to any technology strategy initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How often does your board discuss technology topics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of my clients lament that technology-specific topics are raised, on average, only twice a year at the board level. This level of strategic attention to technology isn&amp;#8217;t just insufficient, it&amp;#8217;s negligent. Boards as well as executive teams must consider the competitive landscape, keeping their eye on not only well-known competitors, but more importantly, from emerging competitors with distruptive technologies. I encourage frequent (at least quarterly) discussions to help keep the focus on competitveness, lest my clients face decimation by a more nible innovator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What technology-related issues are addressed by your leadership?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, most executive teams relegate their technology discussions to the usual Keeping the Lights On (KTLO) issues. These are tasks such as application maintenance, change requests, standard updates, and general systems maintenance. This is at least a $1 Trillion travesty and upwards of 80% of my clients&amp;#8217; IT budgets are spent on KTLO. I help my clients elevate the importance of technology in their organizations from that of a commoditized utility to a strategic value-center. Thinking about that big data or cloud deployment, but you&amp;#8217;ve got KTLO issues? Don&amp;#8217;t do it without talking to me first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have a technologist on your board? How does their presence affect the focus on technology issues?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;#8217;t, you&amp;#8217;re endangering your business. Meaningful technology discussions at the board level are impossible without a technology-literate membership. I&amp;#8217;m not suggesting your CIO or CTO become board members, but I do advocate technology literacy at the board level. I&amp;#8217;ve worked with clients to develop &amp;#8220;tech strategy boot camps&amp;#8221; to achieve literacy in common issues such as data security, agile product management, big data, cloud, and other topics that board members of technology organizations should be conversant in. While this doesn&amp;#8217;t automatically turn novices into experts, it does offer an opportunity to become familiar with core issues affecting business strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What experience do our customers expect, and how can we better delight them?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work with a number of e-commerce clients. They all face constant pressure from the likes of Apple, Amazon, and others to provide an insanely convenient and personal experience. Competing with these retail juggernauts, expecting to beat them at their own game is quixotic. Instead, we create disruptive programs to delight customers through innovative approaches to convenience and service. More traditional companies, such as banks, are deepening their investments in big data and analytics technologies that leverage social, location, and other data to attract and retain customers, both online and in brick and mortar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How agile is our business? Can we deliver high-value impact at low cost and risk?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often describe two dimensions of business agility: strategic and operational. Strategic agility could be, for example, the speed with with a third-party technology can be integrated into an existing system. Business agility would be a measure such as time to market. These two dimensions produce a measure I call &lt;strong&gt;Agile Leverage&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the degree to which an organization can quickly deliver high-value solutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-medium wp-image-873&#34; src=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/agility-300x292.png&#34; alt=&#34;agility&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;292&#34; srcset=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/agility-52x50.png 52w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/agility-300x292.png 300w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/agility.png 333w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can maximize our Agile Leverage via the technology function in several ways. We can reduce the number of systems (I call this &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;minimizing the boxes and arrows&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8220;), improving data quality through standards, adopting agile product/project management methodologies, or enabling resource scaling via the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I help my clients drive both strategic and operational business agility in order to respond quickly and competitively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are you Elastic Enough for Cyber Monday?</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/are-you-elastic-enough-for-cyber-monday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2015 17:56:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/are-you-elastic-enough-for-cyber-monday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine a typical week of traffic to your company&amp;#8217;s web store. This pattern might look a lot like your own traffic, with a peak during the middle of the day, and a slowdown in the middle of the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone wp-image-814 size-full&#34; src=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/Provsioned-Capacity.png&#34; alt=&#34;Provsioned Capacity&#34; width=&#34;721&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; srcset=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/Provsioned-Capacity-300x94.png 300w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/Provsioned-Capacity.png 721w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 721px) 100vw, 721px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this pattern, it becomes really easy to do capacity planning. We can provision, say 15% over what we see our normal peak to be, and be happy with the capacity we have for a while, so long as our traffic matches this pattern. But, we&amp;#8217;re in the first week of November. Check out this traffic graph from one of my e-commerce clients from last November:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone wp-image-817 size-full&#34; src=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/November-Traffic.png&#34; alt=&#34;November Traffic&#34; width=&#34;722&#34; height=&#34;319&#34; srcset=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/November-Traffic-300x133.png 300w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/November-Traffic.png 722w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 722px) 100vw, 722px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graphic represents the entire month of November. We can see big growth at the end of the month with Black Friday and Cyber Monday sales. If we stuck with our &amp;#8220;add 15%&amp;#8221; rule of thumb applied to the spikes, we&amp;#8217;d be in deep trouble for the month. That&amp;#8217;s a lot of wasted capacity and cost &amp;#8211; potentially 76% wasted, with only 24% of it on average utilized for the month. Traditionally, this is how IT has done things. You bought servers for a 6-12 month vision for what growth might look like. So, what&amp;#8217;s the solution to all this waste?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Migrating your infrastructure to the cloud enables elasticity and autoscaling, allowing us to map your capacity directly to end-user needs. We can ensure that at any given point in time, only what you need is provisioned, versus an arbitrary guess at capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my clients&amp;#8217; web stores was hosted on an outdated infrastructure at the end of its lifecycle. Bandwidth was not optimized and the company recognized that the maintenance costs were no longer sustainable. Furthermore, the old website infrastructure was not scalable, preventing the company from supporting new online initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were able to take advantage of the cloud to quickly design and implement a new architecture that could meet workload demands. As a result, we launched their new web store in less than a month. Infrastructure costs were reduced by 50% with improved performance and scalability. Time to market is now close to zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you elastic enough for Cyber Monday?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge Questions for Business Leaders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are you prepared to handle unforeseen spikes in demand?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much money are you wasting in unused capacity?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How quickly can you launch a new offering with your current infrastructure?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 by Mark Richman. All Rights Reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What’s your SCAM Strategy for 2016?</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/whats-your-scam-strategy-for-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 14:20:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/whats-your-scam-strategy-for-2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;wp-image-776 alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM.png&#34; alt=&#34;SCAM&#34; width=&#34;328&#34; height=&#34;314&#34; srcset=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM-52x50.png 52w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM-300x287.png 300w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM.png 790w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 328px) 100vw, 328px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’re in Q4, your technology strategy for 2016 should be well formed. So what’s your plan for SCAM? The Social, Cloud, Analytics, and Mobile (SCAM) stack presents a framework in which organizations can align marketing and technical efforts with a customer-centric strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;social-media-is-the-new-crm&#34;&gt;Social Media is the New CRM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have an innate need for affiliation. We join clubs, professional associations, play sports, and even practice our religions, to one degree or another, in order to satisfy this need. Social media is the modern extension of this community-building. We friend, tweet, pin, share, and like; we are not only expressing our individuality online, but also identifying with groups and brands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s all well and good for sharing cat videos and pictures of your kids, right? &lt;strong&gt;WRONG&lt;/strong&gt;. Social media is a powerful tool to engage your existing customers, and attract new ones, all by capitalizing on their need for affiliation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.noahfleming.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Noah Fleming&lt;/a&gt; writes about community in his book &lt;em&gt;Evergreen&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;#8220;as our customers are becoming more interconnected, they are naturally beginning to build elements of community on their own. Furthermore, if you don&amp;#8217;t create a strong customer community, you can be guaranteed that your competitors will.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional Customer Relationship Management (CRM) systems are transactional in nature. They collect data on customers, transactions, and contact histories. &lt;strong&gt;Social CRM&lt;/strong&gt; allows companies to directly interact with customers &lt;em&gt;en masse&lt;/em&gt;, observe how they communicate with each other, and gauge sentiment about your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media isn&amp;#8217;t just for marketers either. Inbound customer service also leverages social media, offering customers a deeper sense of connectedness than an 800 number or a contact form on your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my clients is the CEO/Owner of an online vitamin supplement company. We were discussing how his larger competitors engaged with customers using social media. While these companies had a team of customer service folks monitoring social media, and interacting with customers, they were too big for their CEO to respond personally. I suggested this was an opportunity for him to &lt;strong&gt;differentiate&lt;/strong&gt; by being directly accessible by his customers via social media. He quickly discovered that he could more quickly obtain customer information than waiting passively for new sales to come in. Learning his customers’ demographics through social media analytics (more on that later) allowed him to save money on advertising campaigns that targeted the wrong segments. Talking with me on Twitter as &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mrichman&#34;&gt;@mrichman&lt;/a&gt; instead of promoting at me with an ad goes a long way to building trust and loyalty through transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cloud&#34;&gt;Cloud&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All organizations are under increasing pressure to maximize their return on technology investment. As budgets shift funds from IT to marketing, the IT organization seeks to save costs. Leveraging a cloud provider, as opposed to maintaining on-premise infrastructure, takes advantage of economies of scale to consume more computing power at lower costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving to the cloud allows for investment using operational expenditures (OPEX), rather than capital expenditures (CAPEX). CFOs no longer concern themselves with depreciating assets, and large lump-sum investments in infrastructure. This approach &lt;strong&gt;frees cash&lt;/strong&gt; for investment in other areas of the business, and reduces the footprint of the IT department as a cost center in the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of my clients are e-commerce companies, and often have to prepare their infrastructure for peaks in traffic. They usually do this by purchasing far more equipment than is needed for typical demand, and often hosting in redundant data centers to mitigate the risk of downtime. Cloud environments allow for &lt;strong&gt;flexible computing power &lt;/strong&gt;that scales on-demand, paying for only what is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security concerns, maintenance, and upgrades account for significant investment in both service agreements and labor. Many cloud infrastructures eliminate or greatly reduce the constant demand for mundane maintenance tasks. Cloud providers with more specialized staff and a greater focus on security can offer CIOs peace of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite reason to move to the cloud is &lt;strong&gt;speed&lt;/strong&gt;. What used to take weeks or even months to spec out, order, provision, and configure, and can now be done in hours or less. This allows organizations to rapidly respond to changes in market demand, and the organization can better avoid the losing proposition of an on-premise physical infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;analytics&#34;&gt;Analytics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, “big data” is all the rage. But all the data in the world is useless if it’s not relevant and actionable. That’s where analytics come in. Your data can come from a wide variety of sources, from social media, e-commerce transactions, website traffic, financial reports, and so on. We’re able to do more than just track clicks now. We can infer relationships between customers and our products and services, and make predictions about their behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working with a number of clients to develop 1:1 marketing programs (also called “one-off” marketing) using historical transaction data. Using analytics tools (often more than one), I look at repeat vs. non-repeat customers, time of day or week, and geographic location in order to segment the customer base. Using this data, we can tailor email campaigns, intercept promotions, and product recommendations to a specific customer’s shopping preferences. Ultimately, this not only increases conversion rates, but also average order value and purchase frequency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mobile&#34;&gt;Mobile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your web strategy is not mobile-first, you&amp;#8217;re doing it wrong. Over half of all web searches are now from mobile devices. Optimizing your website for mobility or having a native application can take advantage of your customers&amp;#8217; location and identity, for example, allowing for a more customized experience. Providing mobile-optimized productivity applications to your workforce will also enable them to be more productive. Many users now have three or more mobile devices &amp;#8211; smartphones, tablets, laptops, and even watches. It&amp;#8217;s more important than ever to target these devices as first-class citizens as part of your technology strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;challenge-questions-for-leaders&#34;&gt;Challenge Questions for Leaders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In what ways does your social media and social CRM strategy engage more prospects and customers, and build a community?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is your enterprise architecture equipped to support SCAM challenges?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can your software development process keep up with the rapidly evolving SCAM landscape?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does your team have the tools, skills, and processes in place to execute your SCAM strategy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CIO should become the CDO</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/the-cio-should-become-the-cdo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 16:33:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/the-cio-should-become-the-cdo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div&gt;
  The role of CIO as Chief &lt;em&gt;Infrastructure&lt;/em&gt; Officer is becoming increasingly irrelevant. IT budgets have shifted to Marketing. Corporate infrastructure is moving to the cloud. So what&amp;#8217;s left? &lt;strong&gt;Data&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-the-chief-data-officer&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enter the Chief Data Officer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Data belongs to the business, not just to IT. The CDO represents these business interests. If the CIO&amp;#8217;s job is simply to keep the lights on, that&amp;#8217;s not something the rest of the business will relate to. If CIOs are to survive, they must evolve, much like the technology for which they have been responsible.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Business intelligence, data analytics, and the value delivered to the business from SCAM (social, cloud, analytics, mobile) will become the primary driver of strategy. We already see this transformation occurring, and CMOs continue to wrestle away not only dollars, but also organizational ownership of the customer. The CMO becomes the CDO&amp;#8217;s best customer.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-cdo-is-a-hybrid-executive&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The CDO is a Hybrid Executive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The most effective CDO will be a &lt;i&gt;hybrid&lt;/i&gt; executive. Often graduating from a CIO or CTO role, their responsibilities will overlap several disciplines:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decision Management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Digital Transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The CDO is a transformational leader, driving business value by integrating emerging technologies with external marketing and customer facing initiatives with internal processes and applications.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-the-cio-can-thrive&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How the CIO can Thrive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  The successful CIO will be the one who can take their organization and gear it toward the ability to program infrastructure as code, and serve new application development, driven by social, cloud, analytics, and mobile.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;challenge-questions-for-leaders&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge Questions for Leaders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What opportunities do you have for creating and enhancing the business value of data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your strategy for responding to SCAM (social, cloud, analytics, mobile) requirements of the business?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will you reshape the business to take advantage of data and technology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All Rights Reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Realtime Voice of the Customer</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/realtime-voice-of-the-customer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 16:04:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/realtime-voice-of-the-customer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been working with my best clients on integrating realtime Voice of the Customer (VoC) technologies into their e-commerce operations. The results have been enlightening and profitable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started with e-commerce systems around 2003, the industry was still in its infancy, and many customers still followed up online orders with multiple confirmation phone calls, or would use a vendor&amp;#8217;s website to get their phone number to place an order. This seems archaic now, just a few years later, when almost nobody picks up the phone to make a purchase. As e-commerce presences grew, the dual phone/web channels could not scale, so the direct and real time feedback of the customer was often lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we capture the Voice of the Customer, gather comments, and learn about opportunities for improvement if we don&amp;#8217;t speak to them anymore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E-commerce vendors developed email-based surveys to fill the gap left by waning telephone sales. These surveys are sent anywhere from the time of order confirmation to several days after delivery. The customer would complete the survey at their leisure, or not at all. Much of the shopping experience itself is usually out of mind by the time an email survey is completed. Over time, these have become little more than noise in a customer&amp;#8217;s inbox, and not very actionable by vendors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not particularly useful to capture the &lt;strong&gt;shopping experience&lt;/strong&gt; itself, email surveys are still effective in a couple of cases. Major vendors, Amazon included, use email surveys to solicit feedback on the products themselves, packaging quality, or shipping speed. Most customers, however, never fill these out unless there is something negative to report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we capture the essence of the customer&amp;#8217;s shopping experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exit Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more immediate feedback, exit surveys are usually placed on the order confirmation page, or when navigating away from this page. Customers&amp;#8217; shopping experience is still fresh in their mind, and both kudos and frustrations are more readily captured. This can also serve as an effective diagnostic tool for any technical problems with a website. I worked with one client, a $400M online retailer, to implement on-page exit surveys, and the results were astounding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their support number would occasionally ring with a customer complaint of checkout issues, only to have the order completed over the phone. This event would never get escalated to the web team for investigation. Over time, these problems just festered until a major promotion went out, when the phone rang nonstop due to shopping cart glitches. The exit survey was directed to the web team, not customer service, and issues were triaged in realtime. The root cause of the website issues was corrected, and &lt;strong&gt;conversion rate improved dramatically&lt;/strong&gt; in a week. No more hours wasted scratching your head over funnel abandon rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realtime Chat&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web-based realtime chat is a terrific innovation for customers to speak to a live person, and comfortably ask questions and give feedback where a phone call is inconvenient or time consuming. Some customers are shy, or have language issues, and typing is just easier for them. Unless you&amp;#8217;re particularly short staffed, this is a fantastic tool, and there&amp;#8217;s no downside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intercept Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I absolutely LOVE these. I use them on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my own website&lt;/a&gt;. Unlike email or exit surveys, you can get realtime feedback from visitors who &lt;strong&gt;chose not to buy&lt;/strong&gt;. These surveys typically take the form of a popup, and ask just a couple of key questions about the shopping experience. I also set them up to capture email addresses for lead generation. I&amp;#8217;ve also set them up to capture Net Promoter Score (NPS), demographic information, or to leak promotion codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often hear concerns about the intrusive nature of these popups, and whether or not they increase bounce rates. Better tools are typically more passive and configurable, appearing only at the most opportune time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we love hearing from customers who spent money, we also need to hear from those who don&amp;#8217;t. You&amp;#8217;re not going to get these insights any other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you hear your customers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amazon’s Outage and your Customers</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/amazons-outage-and-your-customers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 16:13:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/amazons-outage-and-your-customers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past Sunday around 6am ET, &lt;a href=&#34;http://aws.amazon.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Amazon Web Services&lt;/a&gt; had a mega outage, affecting millions of customers worldwide. Amazon Web Services (AWS) is Amazon&amp;#8217;s global cloud computing infrastructure business unit. AWS powers many popular websites including Netflix, Pinterest, Expedia, IMDB, Reddit, and more. Many of my own clients rely on AWS services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple AWS systems failed simultaneously: DynamoDB, Cognito, and CloudWatch. The latter, CloudWatch, is Amazon&amp;#8217;s own cloud monitoring platform. So, the system used to monitor their own cloud went offline, unable to alert on its offline status. Everyone assumed things were humming along until applications relying on AWS services began to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more Software-as-a-Service (SaaS) companies rely on cloud hosting providers like AWS for their infrastructure. When an outage strikes, it&amp;#8217;s not localized like the power company. The whole world feels it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One popular service in my area is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shipt.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Shipt&lt;/a&gt;, an on-demand grocery delivery service, which uses AWS. Customers were able to place orders, but never received their groceries. Shipt started receiving lots of angry Facebook messages, tweets, and emails. Nobody was manning the phones at 6am on a Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outage was resolved after several hours, but most end customers were unaware of the root cause of their favorite sites&amp;#8217; downtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think customers understand that websites can go down. They just don&amp;#8217;t want to be surprised. Sunday&amp;#8217;s event was about lack of information. When you have to Google news sites to see if a website or app is having problems, that&amp;#8217;s a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SaaS companies, like the ones affected by AWS&amp;#8217;s outage, are generally powerless to resolve underlying issues with their cloud provider. So, they need to be far more proactive in customer notification when problems arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s nothing more embarrassing and trust-killing than finding out from your customers that your website is having problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve implemented many third-party and custom monitoring solutions for my clients. One client, a $400M online retailer, had frequent issues with its infrastructure provider, and I delivered a monitoring solution that would notify the marketing team of outages. They could quickly get in front of the issue by posting a notice on the website of checkout issues, and were on call to respond to social media inquiries. This one change stopped most customer service calls, and rebuilt trust with customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acquiring new customers is far more expensive than keeping existing ones. Online businesses should focus on how proactively they handle outages. The customers will trust you and stick around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What steps are you taking to respond to outages and build trust?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Postscript: As I write this, Skype is offline globally most of the day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All Rights Reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Success with Offshore Teams</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/success-with-offshore-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2015 03:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/success-with-offshore-teams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While a steadily growing number of organizations have been moving their resources offshore, it still remains an involved, high-risk decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Most companies consider moving at least some of their workload offshore for cost reduction and “follow the sun” coverage for support staff. I’ve worked with companies of all sizes to integrate offshore teams, and what I’ve found interesting is the common challenges they have. Most notably, they cite while labor costs are lower, product quality decreases, and projects take longer to complete. As a consequence, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;onshore rework&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;to correct offshore defects erodes the cost savings offered by offshoring. Projects take longer to complete, deadlines are missed, and team morale suffers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pride and Prejudice&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;One client of mine, a publicly traded e-commerce company, engaged a team in India to handle bug fixes and some new development work. The team here in the US thumbed their noses at the idea, steadfast in their prejudice that “those people in India” lacked the skill to do the work. The onshore team viewed the offshore team as a threat to their jobs, and the onshore didn’t participate enthusiastically in the relationship.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;I insisted that the offshore team was not there to steal their jobs, but rather to free them from less interesting work. The onshore team could then focus on higher value projects, where their expensive skills and institutional knowledge of the company could best be capitalized upon. In addition, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;core development&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;was kept onshore, where at least one leader/senior developer was responsible. Without a control like this, it&amp;#8217;s impossible to know if the product you&amp;#8217;re receiving from offshore is of any quality.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communication Complexity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;This is the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;number one reason&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;why offshoring will fail. With a team half a world and half a day away, there is little overlap in the teams’ work days in which to share information. Here is where a solid process, and the collaboration tools to enable it are most valuable.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Here are some tools and techniques that work for my clients:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Minimize dependencies between onshore and offshore resources. Your expensive onshore resources shouldn’t be blocked while waiting for offshore folks to complete tasks.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Use great collaboration tools. Basecamp for less technical teams, YouTrack or JIRA for project and task management, Snagit or Jing for screen captures, Dropbox or OneDrive for file sharing, and so on. There are nearly limitless choices here.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Treat your offshore resources as if they were local. Ensure they are always included in communications, meetings, or other relevant events. If you act as if they’re conscripted labor, then you will get exactly the kinds of behaviors back that you have induced—transactional, low-quality work with little documentation from a generally unmotivated workforce.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Never let your onshore team refer to your offshore team as “them.” Seriously, it helps.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose the right offshore partner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;When selecting an offshore vendor, seek a partner that understands and adheres to agile practices such as test-driven development and continuous integration testing. The remote team also needs to be managed locally. That is, they need they need a local leader that they report to. This further minimizes communication complexity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get the right people on the bus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Product Managers at home must understand iterative and progressive development, minimal viable product, and how to prioritize a product backlogs. You want very short sprints (1-2 weeks long) and tight feedback loops. It&amp;#8217;s not about having someone offshore that never makes a single mistake, it&amp;#8217;s that the mistakes must be easily found and quickly fixed. And for that, you need practical use of Agile tools and techniques. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apply these same tactics both onshore and offshore.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Success, not perfection, is an incremental process. If you stick to these basic assumptions, you should be able to work offshore with great results. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com&#34;&gt;Give me a call&lt;/a&gt;, and I can help you choose what’s best for your team.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All Rights Reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictive Analytics for E-Commerce</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/predictive-analytics-e-commerce/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2014 14:00:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/predictive-analytics-e-commerce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re like most online retailers, you face these common challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Competition in similar verticals
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      High marketing budgets
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      High cost of customer acquisition
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      High Customer attrition
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Low profit margins
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Assess your situation by answering the following questions:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      How do I lower my cost of acquisition?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Which factors can drive my customers towards repeat purchase?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      How can I increase the effectiveness of marketing campaigns?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Which assortment sales can improve my margins?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      How can I increase average order value (AOV)?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      How do I personalize my campaigns for maximum response?
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  There are many types of data available to you to address these challenges. In order to effectively target your marketing campaigns, you must effectively collect, analyze, and apply these data. Here are some potential data sources that you can leverage:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Social Media Streams
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Referring Websites
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Customer Transactions
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Web Logs
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Clickstream Data
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Customer Demographics
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Customer Service Logs
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are you currently aggregating these disparate data sources in order to optimize for sales? It is not enough to simply ask the data “what happened?” or even “why did it happen?” The most value can be derived from asking “what &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; happen?” (prediction) and then &lt;strong&gt;making it happen&lt;/strong&gt; (prescription). This approach will move your focus from hindsight to foresight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a predictive model, you will have increased confidence as to when customers will abandon a transaction, accept product recommendations, enroll in a continuity program, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prescriptive models, based on continued observations of predictive data, will allow you to tune your campaigns for maximum conversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staples, for example, executes over 1,500 multichannel campaigns annually based on over 25 million customer records. Jim Foreman, Director of Circulation and Analytics at Staples, reports &amp;#8220;We did a financial analysis of the implementation, and we found that we were getting an internal rate of return of 137%”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How would you like an ROI like that?!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the phases of the analytics life cycle, and some example models I can help you use to make better decisions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Customer Acquisition
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Acquisition Response Models
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Customer Value Scoring Models
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Customer Profiling &amp; Segmentation
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Campaign Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Customer Management
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Profitability Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Channel Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Call center analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Market Mix Modeling
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Relationship Expansion
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Loyalty (attrition) analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Cross-sell/Upsell Modeling
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Campaign Effectiveness
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Product Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Propensity Modeling
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Customer Retention
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Personalization
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Product Affinity
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Satisfaction &amp; Loyalty Indices
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Lifetime Value (LTV) Prediction
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  Voice of the Customer Analytics
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Survey Analytics
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Social Media Analytics
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Sentiment Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Promoter/Detractor Analysis
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Text Analytics
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  How can you get from descriptive to &lt;i&gt;predictive&lt;/i&gt; analytics, and take your campaigns to the next level?
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Richman Test: 12 Steps to Better E-Commerce</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/the-richman-test-12-steps-to-better-e-commerce/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 15:08:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/the-richman-test-12-steps-to-better-e-commerce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I developed a highly focused test to rate the quality of an e-commerce organization&amp;#8217;s effectiveness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you know who your ideal customer is?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you market where your ideal customer hangs out?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you selling what your customers *really* want?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can your customer easily find you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can your customer easily find their product of interest on your website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you offer multiple payment methods?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you offer multiple shipping methods?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you segment your customers into lists, and email those lists regularly?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have an affiliate program?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have a continuity program?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you perform multivariate testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have a complete suite of KPI reports?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A score of 12 is perfect, but at 9 or lower your e-commerce organization has serious problems! In practice, most online retailers operate at a 5 or so, and need _serious_ help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In which of these areas are you excelling? &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com:1313/contact&#34;&gt;Share your story&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In which areas could you be more effective? &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com:1313/contact&#34;&gt;I can help&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>