<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Uncategorized on Mark Richman Consulting</title>
    <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/uncategorized/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Uncategorized on Mark Richman Consulting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 16:11:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.markrichman.com:1313/categories/uncategorized/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Team Performance Self-Diagnostic</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/team-performance-self-diagnostic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 16:11:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/team-performance-self-diagnostic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Very often, I&amp;#8217;m contacted by prospective clients who are seeking &amp;#8220;help with &lt;em&gt;&lt;insert technology here&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#8221; After some discussion, the truth often surfaces. While clients might &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; help with a particular technology, what they usually &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; is completely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of my best clients believed that implementing a popular technology, product, or process will cure all that ails them. In reality, it&amp;#8217;s one of many possible team performance issues that require correction, and not a technology problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many of the following issues resonate with you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frequently missed deadlines and commitments, either internally or externally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cutting features or adding people to a late project in order to make a date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skipping testing steps to save time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reopening bugs that were marked as tested, but in reality were not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frequent regression testing failures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team members working overtime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developers and testers don&amp;#8217;t communicate or work as a team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &amp;#8220;brilliant jerk&amp;#8221; on the team whose toxicity erodes team morale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8220;Job security through obscurity&amp;#8221; where developers write vague, uncomment, or hard-to-understand code in order to maintain their perceived indispensibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blame shifting on a team or across teams or departments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source code control and configuration management are unusued or used minimally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frequent rewrites of major pieces of functionality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_factor&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;bus factor&lt;/a&gt; is 0 or 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poor root cause analysis or plus/delta assesments after major outages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list is greatly abbreviated, as these issues are seemingly endless. However, they represent some of the most expensive problems that face your organization. What&amp;#8217;s interesting is that there are few, if any, technologies or products that can solve these problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you experience &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of the issues on this list, &lt;strong&gt;you need help&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2016 by Mark Richman. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid Innovation Self-Diagnostic</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/rapid-innovation-self-diagnostic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 18:13:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/rapid-innovation-self-diagnostic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;#8217;s preventing your ability to rapidly innovate?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long does it take you to deliver even a single line of code change into production?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long does it take you to bring a new product to market?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How often do you fail to meet commitments to both customers and business partners?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you want to lower the cost of bringing your products to market?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have a deeper backlog of work than you have resources?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What level of transparency does your process have?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much does support work interrupt your new product development?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does the quality of your products suffer because of all of the above?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d love to hear your responses!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2016 by Mark Richman. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mr. McFeely’s Speedy Delivery</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/mr-mcfeelys-speedy-delivery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 18:08:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/mr-mcfeelys-speedy-delivery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-956 alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/mr-mcfeely-website-header-image-300x112.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Mr. McFeely&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;112&#34; /&gt;When I was a kid, I loved &lt;em&gt;Mister Rogers&amp;#8217; Neighborhood&lt;/em&gt;. My favorite character, aside from Mr. Rogers, of course, was Mr. McFeely, the Speedy Delivery man. Mr. McFeely&amp;#8217;s one and only job was to deliver life lessons in the form of parcels to the neighborhood. When working with my clients, I aspire to be like Mr. McFeely, helping to develop the people, processes, tools, and techniques to enable the &lt;strong&gt;speedy delivery&lt;/strong&gt; of ever evolving solutions to their customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I evangelize the principle of delivering working software quickly and frequently. Many organizations struggle or fail to implement this principle because it&amp;#8217;s the one that requires the most organizational change. There are two critical components to the success of Speedy Delivery: Continuous Integration (CI), and Business-Driven Development (BDD). The CI process enables early defect detection, and BDD allows the satisfaction of business-driven requirements, as opposed to technology-driven ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who resist this change are often gatekeepers, whose job exists solely to enforce the very processes that hold your progress back. If these draconian processes are really just administrative exercises in filling out forms, checking boxes, and gathering signatures, then it&amp;#8217;s likely unnecessary overhead. For organizations wary of automated processes, I suggest there is a way to retain that human oversight. Empower the former gatekeeper to own the new automated processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often ask clients this question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How long does it take you to deliver even a single line of code change into production?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the answer is more than a day or so then there&amp;#8217;s a lot of work to do for continuous integration and delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2016 by Mark Richman. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scalability: A Million Dollar Question</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/scalability-a-million-dollar-question/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 14:28:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/scalability-a-million-dollar-question/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-944 alignright&#34; src=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Untitled-300x182.png&#34; alt=&#34;Scalability&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;182&#34; srcset=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Untitled-300x182.png 300w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Untitled.png 662w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re anything like my clients, you spend a lot of time trying to do these two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximize the productivity of your limited staff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximize the performance of your software systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As your business grows, both problems become increasingly difficult &amp;#8211; and expensive &amp;#8211; to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, I want to address the first point &amp;#8211; your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extensive &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Assessments-Benchmarks-Addison-Wesley-Information-Technology/dp/0201485427&#34;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; has shown that productivity drains are a direct result of inefficient processes. Team size does not matter as much as you might think. I&amp;#8217;ve seen small teams perform horribly, and big teams move nimbly, all due to their ability to scale up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what makes a team (of any size) scale most efficiently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key is to shift focus away from the people and onto the product. I know, this sounds counterintuitive, but stick with me for a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your product, or more precisely, the code that makes up your software product, can be managed with precision, unlike your people. Focus on motivating your people, not managing them. Ultimately, they will produce more with higher quality. Then, you ship whatever is ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this early and often. Prioritize instead of planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do I maintain control?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glad you asked. Here are the ways you still control the process:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You own the product backlog, and the prioritization of its items&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You allocate tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You set time and budget limits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You control the code, feature branches, and acceptance testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You enforce standards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this help me scale up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process is fast. You release when you’re ready, as often as you’re ready. It also works well with distributed teams. You can add many more contributors without a planning or testing bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I have to change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re already a Scrum or Kanban shop, then very little. If your teams are already productive, then they won’t notice much process change. If they are unproductive, then you should &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/contact/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;give me a call&lt;/a&gt;, and we&amp;#8217;ll fix that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my next article, I will discuss the second point &amp;#8211; software performance and scalability.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What’s your SCAM Strategy for 2016?</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/whats-your-scam-strategy-for-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 14:20:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/whats-your-scam-strategy-for-2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;wp-image-776 alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM.png&#34; alt=&#34;SCAM&#34; width=&#34;328&#34; height=&#34;314&#34; srcset=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM-52x50.png 52w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM-300x287.png 300w, http://www.markrichman.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/SCAM.png 790w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 328px) 100vw, 328px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’re in Q4, your technology strategy for 2016 should be well formed. So what’s your plan for SCAM? The Social, Cloud, Analytics, and Mobile (SCAM) stack presents a framework in which organizations can align marketing and technical efforts with a customer-centric strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;social-media-is-the-new-crm&#34;&gt;Social Media is the New CRM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have an innate need for affiliation. We join clubs, professional associations, play sports, and even practice our religions, to one degree or another, in order to satisfy this need. Social media is the modern extension of this community-building. We friend, tweet, pin, share, and like; we are not only expressing our individuality online, but also identifying with groups and brands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s all well and good for sharing cat videos and pictures of your kids, right? &lt;strong&gt;WRONG&lt;/strong&gt;. Social media is a powerful tool to engage your existing customers, and attract new ones, all by capitalizing on their need for affiliation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.noahfleming.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Noah Fleming&lt;/a&gt; writes about community in his book &lt;em&gt;Evergreen&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;#8220;as our customers are becoming more interconnected, they are naturally beginning to build elements of community on their own. Furthermore, if you don&amp;#8217;t create a strong customer community, you can be guaranteed that your competitors will.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional Customer Relationship Management (CRM) systems are transactional in nature. They collect data on customers, transactions, and contact histories. &lt;strong&gt;Social CRM&lt;/strong&gt; allows companies to directly interact with customers &lt;em&gt;en masse&lt;/em&gt;, observe how they communicate with each other, and gauge sentiment about your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media isn&amp;#8217;t just for marketers either. Inbound customer service also leverages social media, offering customers a deeper sense of connectedness than an 800 number or a contact form on your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my clients is the CEO/Owner of an online vitamin supplement company. We were discussing how his larger competitors engaged with customers using social media. While these companies had a team of customer service folks monitoring social media, and interacting with customers, they were too big for their CEO to respond personally. I suggested this was an opportunity for him to &lt;strong&gt;differentiate&lt;/strong&gt; by being directly accessible by his customers via social media. He quickly discovered that he could more quickly obtain customer information than waiting passively for new sales to come in. Learning his customers’ demographics through social media analytics (more on that later) allowed him to save money on advertising campaigns that targeted the wrong segments. Talking with me on Twitter as &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mrichman&#34;&gt;@mrichman&lt;/a&gt; instead of promoting at me with an ad goes a long way to building trust and loyalty through transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cloud&#34;&gt;Cloud&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All organizations are under increasing pressure to maximize their return on technology investment. As budgets shift funds from IT to marketing, the IT organization seeks to save costs. Leveraging a cloud provider, as opposed to maintaining on-premise infrastructure, takes advantage of economies of scale to consume more computing power at lower costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving to the cloud allows for investment using operational expenditures (OPEX), rather than capital expenditures (CAPEX). CFOs no longer concern themselves with depreciating assets, and large lump-sum investments in infrastructure. This approach &lt;strong&gt;frees cash&lt;/strong&gt; for investment in other areas of the business, and reduces the footprint of the IT department as a cost center in the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of my clients are e-commerce companies, and often have to prepare their infrastructure for peaks in traffic. They usually do this by purchasing far more equipment than is needed for typical demand, and often hosting in redundant data centers to mitigate the risk of downtime. Cloud environments allow for &lt;strong&gt;flexible computing power &lt;/strong&gt;that scales on-demand, paying for only what is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security concerns, maintenance, and upgrades account for significant investment in both service agreements and labor. Many cloud infrastructures eliminate or greatly reduce the constant demand for mundane maintenance tasks. Cloud providers with more specialized staff and a greater focus on security can offer CIOs peace of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite reason to move to the cloud is &lt;strong&gt;speed&lt;/strong&gt;. What used to take weeks or even months to spec out, order, provision, and configure, and can now be done in hours or less. This allows organizations to rapidly respond to changes in market demand, and the organization can better avoid the losing proposition of an on-premise physical infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;analytics&#34;&gt;Analytics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, “big data” is all the rage. But all the data in the world is useless if it’s not relevant and actionable. That’s where analytics come in. Your data can come from a wide variety of sources, from social media, e-commerce transactions, website traffic, financial reports, and so on. We’re able to do more than just track clicks now. We can infer relationships between customers and our products and services, and make predictions about their behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working with a number of clients to develop 1:1 marketing programs (also called “one-off” marketing) using historical transaction data. Using analytics tools (often more than one), I look at repeat vs. non-repeat customers, time of day or week, and geographic location in order to segment the customer base. Using this data, we can tailor email campaigns, intercept promotions, and product recommendations to a specific customer’s shopping preferences. Ultimately, this not only increases conversion rates, but also average order value and purchase frequency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mobile&#34;&gt;Mobile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your web strategy is not mobile-first, you&amp;#8217;re doing it wrong. Over half of all web searches are now from mobile devices. Optimizing your website for mobility or having a native application can take advantage of your customers&amp;#8217; location and identity, for example, allowing for a more customized experience. Providing mobile-optimized productivity applications to your workforce will also enable them to be more productive. Many users now have three or more mobile devices &amp;#8211; smartphones, tablets, laptops, and even watches. It&amp;#8217;s more important than ever to target these devices as first-class citizens as part of your technology strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;challenge-questions-for-leaders&#34;&gt;Challenge Questions for Leaders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In what ways does your social media and social CRM strategy engage more prospects and customers, and build a community?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is your enterprise architecture equipped to support SCAM challenges?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can your software development process keep up with the rapidly evolving SCAM landscape?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does your team have the tools, skills, and processes in place to execute your SCAM strategy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When You Need a Technology Advisor</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/when-you-need-a-technology-advisor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 01:31:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/when-you-need-a-technology-advisor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re an established business looking to raise the bar, or a startup delivering new technology to market, you need expert knowledge and experience to advise you. In this article, I’m going to discuss what a technology advisor does, and how you’ll be far better off working with one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who works with a technology advisor?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business owners and technology executives&lt;/strong&gt; need to make quick but informed decisions. Top line revenue growth, and bottom line profit are key drivers. A technology advisor can bring their considerable expertise to bear in supplementing understanding, finding value, and accelerating learning. These business leaders can take advantage of proven approaches to common challenges, and discover value in new ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investors&lt;/strong&gt; often call upon a technology advisor when evaluating a new opportunity. These engagements are called technical due diligence. If an investor is going to spend millions to acquire a startup, or take one public, it must be certain of the content it’s buying, and how quickly it can monetize the investment.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Startup founders&lt;/strong&gt;, unlike traditional business owners and investors, have a vision, but often lack the expertise to realize it. A technology advisor can help guide and launch a new venture through both strategic and tactical expertise.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you need a technology advisor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;A technology advisor can help accelerate business growth by applying the following expertise:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Develop business plans, focusing on cost and time estimates for delivering a solution&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Create prototypes to help communicate ideas to investors and business partners&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Help select the appropriate technologies and vendors to realize business goals&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Guide the software development process, ensuring repeatable delivery of high-quality products and features&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Evaluate staffing needs and help source, interview, and select candidates at all levels of the organization&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Improve individual and team performance through training and coaching&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How you’re better off when I’m gone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;One of the best reasons why startups call me for advice is the tremendous value I provide &lt;strong&gt;without diluting the firm’s equity&lt;/strong&gt;. Many early stage startup founders don’t want a full time CIO or CTO, and will call upon me tactically while preserving the value of their shares.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;I also work with established firms to help select technology delivery partners, both onshore and offshore. I provide an objective assessment of the capabilities and quality of vendors. Entrusting a third party to help grow a business is daunting. Imagine the &lt;strong&gt;cost of making a mistake&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;For individuals, I help accelerate learning and and improve life balance. New ways of thinking, tools, techniques, and processes produce &lt;strong&gt;dramatic results&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All Rights Reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tight Lips Sink Ships</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/tight-lips-sink-ships/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 15:23:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/tight-lips-sink-ships/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During Word War II, the US Office of War Information coined the phrase “Loose Lips Sink Ships” in an effort to mitigate the risk of leaking information to enemy spies. While this tactic is useful during wartime, it can serve to hurt your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I mean here is sinking your ship from within by &lt;strong&gt;failing&lt;/strong&gt; to communicate, both early and often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my best clients is a government contractor, providing software systems to to the US military. Over the past year, I have worked with them to customize one of their commercial products for government use. As you might imagine, the compliance requirements are rather stringent, as is the schedule. I sat in on several of their release planning meetings, whose purpose is to ensure the quality of the final deliverables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of one of these meetings, a representative from the marketing department, who had not previously attended, chimed in with a concern over branding. Apparently, several of the software components incorrectly used one of their trademarked brand names. This software had been in development for a year, and the branding was prominently displayed, available for review by the marketing department throughout the development process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software was in lockdown mode, that is, no further changes, and had been signed off internally for delivery to the customer several days later. So why would marketing throw a red flag so late in the game? Their response was, “we told you months ago.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, this spun up the organization at the highest levels. Nobody, except for marketing, seemed to recall this branding directive. I suggested the following, “Should you push back the release to satisfy the marketing department, or proceed with inconsistent branding, and &lt;strong&gt;satisfy the customer&lt;/strong&gt;?” Everyone shut up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software was &lt;strong&gt;released on time&lt;/strong&gt;, without any branding changes. “Sorry, marketing folks, we’ll get your change in the next release,” said my client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what went wrong here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The marketing folks, while correct about the branding issue, failed to &lt;strong&gt;communicate early and often&lt;/strong&gt;. They had a responsibility to the rest of the organization to champion their requirements. The development organization also had a responsibility to &lt;strong&gt;ask the right questions&lt;/strong&gt;. Neither of these happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Failing to effectively communicate within your organization will impact your goals more than any other factor. Not talent. Not effort. Not money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you sinking ships, or keeping the boat afloat?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8211; Mark&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© 2015 Mark Richman. All Rights Reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Establishing Trust in Your Brand</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/establishing-trust-in-your-brand/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2015 16:49:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/establishing-trust-in-your-brand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just bought a new home. Well, new to me anyway. I need to have the entire interior repainted from its current shade of canary yellow to something more&amp;#8230;civilized. So, I’ve been auditioning painting contractors. I figured three competitive estimates would net me something workable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I solicited referrals from friends and colleagues, and even took to Angie’s List for a highly reviewed local company. I gave two a call, and surprisingly, both were available the same day to provide written estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first to arrive was a professionally attired sales rep, in a crisp white dress shirt adorned with the company logo. He came prepared with some basic stats about my home, no doubt sourced from public records. He went directly into his rehearsed pitch, citing the forty years’ experience he has in the business. He offered some “decorating suggestions”, which were transparent upsell questions. Then, we walked my home, and I pointed out areas of concern, and I expressed my ideal outcome. He offered, “I’m not the cheapest.” I never once mentioned budget. He gave me a verbal “soft” quote, and said he’d email me the written proposal the same day, which he did. The price was well above market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second guy came out at the appointed time, in jeans and company polo shirt. He was the owner. He noticed the two paint color samples I had on the wall, with their Sherwin-Williams numbers I had scribbled beneath in paint with my finger. He called out the two color names from memory, unprompted. I was impressed! He told me he was a third-generation painter, and could eyeball most colors in the catalog. As we walked my home, he suggested that we didn’t need to repaint most ceilings, as they were in good condition, and it would be wasted money. Quite the opposite approach to the other guy’s aggressive upsell. He didn’t offer a verbal estimate, and said he wanted to “do his homework” and would email me a quote. He did indeed, and was 30% less expensive that the other vendor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not seek a third estimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While price was indeed part of my decision-making, it was the approach to relationship building that the second vendor took with me which ultimately sealed the deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottom line, he established a &lt;strong&gt;trusting relationship&lt;/strong&gt; with me &lt;strong&gt;before trying to sell me anything&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What level of trust do your customers and clients have in your brand?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;© Mark Richman 2015&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Business Objectives to Drive Technology Projects</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/using-business-objectives-to-drive-technology-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 16:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/using-business-objectives-to-drive-technology-projects/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;When I meet with clients for the first time, they often present me with a project concept and requirements already defined. Measures of success are usually loose or absent, but a firm deadline is common. The client often jumps right to cost, scope, or some other set of variables they believe are of primary importance. Here I hit the brakes, and work with the client to discover the real problem the project is trying to solve. I won’t discuss software at all. No methodologies, no processes, no code, no products. The only thing I’ll discuss is the client’s business objectives, not technical ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clients are often shocked at my apparent lack of concern about the technical details. We will, of course, discuss them when it makes sense. In order to best serve my clients, I need to understand more about them and their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;discovering-objectives&#34;&gt;Discovering Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ostensibly, it would appear that the business objective for a specific problem (or set of problems) is to just solve that problem. However, business problems usually don’t specify success metrics that a business is trying to achieve. It’s the metrics that we’ll use to determine whether or not the problem has been solved or mitigated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we uncover the business objective? I always establish understanding of the business problem by asking, “What is the business problem that you are trying to solve?” I tend to keep asking, “Why is that a problem?” (rather annoyingly at times) until I get to the money, cost, efficiency, or the regulatory answer. Once I get an answer that involves any of these dimensions, I have the business problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of business problems, restated as objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table style=&#34;border-bottom: solid 1px black;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&#34;border-bottom: solid 1px black;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;background-color: #ddd; color: #000;&#34;&gt;
      Problem
    &lt;/th&gt;
    
    &lt;th style=&#34;background-color: #ddd; color: #000;&#34;&gt;
      Objective
    &lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  
  &lt;tr style=&#34;border-bottom: solid 1px black;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Confidence in current web hosting vendor has declined.
    &lt;/td&gt;
    
    &lt;td&gt;
      Ensure the business’ web presence is uninterrupted regardless of the relationship with a vendor, and implement 24-hour disaster recovery.
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  
  &lt;tr style=&#34;border-bottom: solid 1px black;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Conversion rate on the e-commerce site has declined 20% in the past year. Customer’s can’t easily check out on mobile devices.
    &lt;/td&gt;
    
    &lt;td&gt;
      Redesign the e-commerce storefront to make more effective use of mobile-friendly technology. Minimize the number of steps through checkout on mobile.
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      Customer support is inundated with customer complaints about slow website performance.
    &lt;/td&gt;
    
    &lt;td&gt;
      Implement web performance instrumentation to determine the root cause of poor website performance.
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is critical to understand that objectives are &lt;strong&gt;outcomes not inputs&lt;/strong&gt;. These are not &lt;strong&gt;deliverables&lt;/strong&gt;. I hate that word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;measuring-success&#34;&gt;Measuring Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s always interesting to observe with clients that go through this exercise with me how their solution concept changes. While their vision for a solution may not be the same, they are more confident in our joint ability to solve the business problem, now that the objectives are clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve discovered the business objective, how do we measure success? We need to describe specific outcomes that meet these objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some example success metrics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potential website downtime is below 24 hours, as evidenced by a disaster recovery test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average conversion rate on the e-commerce site has increased by 10%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer support incidents relating to website performance have decreased by 25%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also use the business objectives together with success metrics in order to control scope. Clients often request “bells and whistles” after a project has begun. Regardless of the “cool” factor, if a feature can’t be linked back to one of the stated business objectives, it’s out of scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;assigning-value&#34;&gt;Assigning Value&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is the client’s condition better after we’ve met the business objectives? In other words, what is the solution worth to the client? It could be a quantitative value in dollars, such as “double net profit”, or it could be something more subjective, such as “increased discretionary time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I work with my clients to achieve dramatic results, improve the condition of their business, and make their lives better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hyperproductive Distributed Scrum Teams</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/hyperproductive-distributed-scrum-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2014 16:22:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/hyperproductive-distributed-scrum-teams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jeff Sutherland is one of the co-creators of the Scrum software development process. He and Ken Schwaber invented Scrum in 1993. Since then he has worked with many software companies and IT organizations to extend and enhance this process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Online Shopping Statistics</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/online-shopping-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 13:13:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/online-shopping-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;71% of shoppers expect customer service assistance within 5 minutes

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;47% of shoppers actively seek customer reviews through social media&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A product needs 50 online reviews to raise conversion rate by 4.6%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;81% of shoppers cite social recommendations as directly influential on purchase decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;74% of shoppers abandon carts due to high delivery charges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;75% of shoppers add to their orders to qualify for free shipping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoppers respond to free shipping offers 2x more than price discounts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;55% of cart abandoners spend even more when receiving a cart recovery email&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;59% of shoppers believe a personalized experience makes it easier to find what they are looking for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;56% of shoppers that receive personalized recommendations are more likely to return&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;84% of marketers realize positive ROI from behavioral targeting for personalization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding E-Commerce Conversion</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/understanding-e-commerce-conversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 17:24:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/understanding-e-commerce-conversion/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Your e-commerce investment is a big one. The “if you build it, they will come” approach does not apply. Your traffic is low, and sales are flat. What to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-arent-i-selling-as-much-as-i-could-be&#34;&gt;Why aren’t I selling as much as I could be?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any business, online or brick and mortar, there are certain fundamentals to customer acquisition and conversion that remain constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;establishing-demand&#34;&gt;Establishing Demand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the demand seasonal or is it constant? Is it something people would feel comfortable buying online?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;understanding-the-competition&#34;&gt;Understanding the Competition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are you doing when it comes to competing against common keywords? How strong is their grip of the market? It could be that you have terrible SEO compared to them and people literally can’t find you. At the end of the day, SEO is very much like real life. In real life, you’d want to try to sell on “Main Street”, right? Well, “Main Street” on the internet is claiming the first 4 organic results for your search terms on Google. Try to find this out by using tools like Compete or SimilarSites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;time-on-the-market&#34;&gt;Time on the market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first few weeks that you’ve opened your store might be slow for you. Sometimes it’s important to manage expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;promotion-and-lead-management&#34;&gt;Promotion and Lead Management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are you getting a steady stream of leads? Are you collecting emails? Are you running ads?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-down-to-the-nitty-gritty&#34;&gt;Getting down to the nitty gritty&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-metric-1---conversion-rate&#34;&gt;Key Metric 1 &amp;#8211; Conversion Rate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you getting a lot of site visits but very few conversions? What’s the shopping cart abandonment rate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-metric-2---site-speed&#34;&gt;Key Metric 2 &amp;#8211; Site Speed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your site load speed? The slower it is, the higher your shopping cart abandonment rate and bounce rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-metrics-3--4---time-on-site-and-bounce-rate&#34;&gt;Key Metrics 3 &amp;amp; 4 &amp;#8211; Time on Site and Bounce Rate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whats the average amount of time that people are spending on your website? Is the bounce rate very high? If both of them seem poor &amp;#8211; you’re probably not clearly articulating the value of what your site is selling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pricing&#34;&gt;Pricing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the pricing appropriate? Perhaps you’re selling SKUs which could be found elsewhere on the internet for a cheaper price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;channel-diversity&#34;&gt;Channel Diversity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you selling on multiple channels? Perhaps you shouldn’t just be spending all your time just on the store you built yourself….try selling on eBay, Amazon, Etsy, etc. This is called selling multichannel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;search-engine-and-social-marketing&#34;&gt;Search Engine and Social Marketing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you invested in marketing your website? Where are you marketing it? Are you seeing any return on investment from these marketing channels you’re currently pursuing? You wouldn’t be spending money on Facebook ads if you’re selling rubber gaskets, you’d be advertising on forums where people talk about that kind of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;specialize-and-thrive&#34;&gt;Specialize and Thrive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your niche targeted enough? Perhaps you’re not craving yourself a name for your site as “the destination site for X.” This might be reflected in a lack of variety regarding the products you’re selling. This inevitably will spill over to marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;email-is-king&#34;&gt;Email is King&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you sending customers enough emails? Email is BY FAR the most effective method to convince someone to return to your site. Don’t just sent one &amp;#8211; create drip campaigns. Brand awareness is created by seeing a brand in multiple places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are good places to start. I hope this helps!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can help you grow your business in any of these areas. Please &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markrichman.com:1313/contact/&#34; title=&#34;Contact&#34;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Do IT Projects Really Fail?</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/projects-really-fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2013 17:19:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/projects-really-fail/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I recently experienced my first IT project “failure” in many years. The purpose of this article is partly therapeutic, but also tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful IT project management is critical to enterprise success and to the career growth and success of participating executives, project managers, and project team members. In my case, I served in all three roles. Without divulging too many project details, or the identities of anyone else involved, I will take some creative license with the specifics as I recount my experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many years ago, I read Ed Yourdon’s seminal work, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Death-March-Edition-Edward-Yourdon/dp/013143635X/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Death March&lt;/em&gt; (2003)&lt;/a&gt;, where he explores this phenomenon in great detail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;many of the projects in today’s chaotic business environment involve such intense pressure that they are referred to colloquially as “death-march” projects – i.e., projects whose schedules are so compressed, and/or whose budgets, or resource (people) assignments are so constrained, that the only “obvious” way to succeed is for the entire team to work 16 hours a day, 7 days a week, with no vacations until the project is finished. While the corporate goal of such projects is to overcome impossible odds and achieve miracles, the personal goal of the project manager and team members often shrinks down to mere survival: keeping one’s job, maintaining some semblance of a relationship with one’s spouse and children, and avoiding a heart attack or ulcer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular project involved replacing an e-commerce transactional email system. There were two drivers of this project: 1) the existing e-commerce platform is undergoing replacement by a more capable system, and 2) there is a separate system used for marketing emails (e.g. acquisition and retention). This system is provided by an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Email_service_provider_(marketing)&#34;&gt;Email Service Provider (ESP)&lt;/a&gt;. By leveraging the ESP’s detailed metrics and reporting, the organization would gain greater insight into customer behavior, and consequently run higher converting email campaigns. So far so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project kicked off with a short list of the various transactional emails to be migrated. This included the standard e-commerce emails for order confirmation, ship confirmation, backorder notifications, etc. Since I was porting over the implementation from the web-based shopping cart’s canned emails to the ESP, I needed to use a different source of data to be authoritative for order information. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enterprise_resource_planning&#34;&gt;Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP)&lt;/a&gt; system served just such a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this ERP is rather obscure and dated, and I have, at the time of this writing, not yet received any formal training, either internally or from the vendor. The system documentation is poor, and the vendor is somewhat uncooperative when it comes to the details of its proprietary &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Database_schema&#34;&gt;database schema&lt;/a&gt;. So, I trudged on, implementing the program logic to retrieve the required data to populate email templates in the ESP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of weeks of some of my best &lt;a href=&#34;http://wwww.python.org&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL&#34;&gt;SQL&lt;/a&gt; programming, I had a completed system ready for testing. Since this organization has no QA resources, I felt the onus was on me to not only contrive, but also execute test cases. I was provided with three test orders against which to test my system. The resulting emails delivered successfully, and contained the correct content and values. The legacy emails were disabled, and my system went live. Success!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not so fast…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a week or so, the customer service department began to receive complaints from customers about erroneous emails. In one case the shipping address was incorrect (it displayed the billing address instead), and in another case the order total was incorrect, not taking into consideration a discount which had been applied. I quickly identified, fixed, and deployed the necessary code changes. However, additional complaints of errors trickled in. It was decided that my application be disabled and the legacy system be reactivated until the new e-commerce platform was ready for QA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a subsequent management meeting, my project’s business owner publicly berated me for my lack of quality, and interrogated me as to why he should expect different results after I claim to have the bugs worked out. Now, I really don’t mind criticism, or even a reprimand when deserved, but certainly not in a public forum where other managers and &lt;em&gt;my direct reports&lt;/em&gt; are in attendance. Not cool. Fortunately, the CEO immediately stepped in to defend me. No apologies were ever offered, and I continued on with my work, fixing bugs and preparing for my applications inevitable redeployment. However, this negative interaction ate away at me both emotionally and physically, and that’s no way to work or live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what could I have done differently to mitigate all the above misfortune? Well, there are generally two types of risks when it comes to IT projects: people-related risks and process-related risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;people-related-risks&#34;&gt;People-Related Risks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of top management support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weak commitment of project team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subject matter experts are overscheduled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weak project manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No stakeholder involvement and/or participation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team members lack requisite knowledge and/or skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;process-related-risks&#34;&gt;Process-Related Risks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of documented requirements and/or success criteria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No change control process (change management)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ineffective schedule planning and/or management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communication breakdown among stakeholders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resources assigned to a higher priority project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No business case for the project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at the people-related risks first. I had top management support &amp;#8211; check. Team commitment &amp;#8211; check. Subject matter experts overscheduled? Nope. Project management &amp;#8211; hmmm &amp;#8211; the organization has no project manager. So, my “customer” played the role of PM. There is inherent conflict awaiting right there. A PM’s job is to remove obstacles to ensure project and team success. My biggest obstacle was my lack of knowledge of both the ERP system and the various permutations of customer orders. My “customer” seemed to find my constant inquiries irritating. Perhaps a formal project manager would have taken a different approach than I did for extracting information. But, this leads me to stakeholder involvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to work in an &lt;em&gt;agile methodology&lt;/em&gt;, an environment which is both collaborative and adaptive. My stakeholders seemed to be content, if not &lt;em&gt;insistent&lt;/em&gt; on what we call the &lt;em&gt;waterfall&lt;/em&gt; approach. That is, the requirements are provided (in varying forms of detail and/or quality) and the implementation proceeds until its end with little or no feedback or participation from the customer. This &lt;em&gt;modus operandi&lt;/em&gt; is almost always fraught with failure, either through cost and time overruns, or incorrect and incomplete features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a professional software engineer since 1996, and an amateur one since 1979. Skills were not the issue on this project. Lack of requisite knowledge? Ah ha! Now we’re getting somewhere. An obscure ERP system, poorly documented, with stakeholders who have years of hands-on experience versus a software engineer with domain expertise, but zero knowledge of the critical system in question. With less than 90 days on the job, and no training, required knowledge was clearly lacking. Requests for formal training went ignored, for reasons that are still unclear to me. I’m just going to tell myself it was a budget constraint. The real reason doesn’t much matter now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what about process-related risks? Well, lack of documented requirements certainly stand out. More often than not, projects like this one, where one is replacing one system with another to perform a similar function, have few requirements. Most often, the requirements will be a sentence like, “make it work &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; like the old one, except we need the flux capacitor to interface with the forced quantum singularity.” This is comically anemic when it comes to specifics &amp;#8211; success criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-did-i-do-wrong&#34;&gt;What did I do wrong?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I got past my technical hurdles when it came to the ERP system, and relaunched a defect-free system. No harm done. However, this could have all been much more drama-free. I should have been far more vocal when it came to my ignorance of the ERP system’s internals. This may have been the static with which my requests for training were met, or equally likely, engineer’s pride. I was too proud to ask for more help. This was unfortunately reinforced by my stakeholders’ frustration with my repeated questions. More importantly, I feel the success criteria of the project should have been far more elaborate from the project’s inception. What does “does it work?” look like? Also, since the organization lacks QA resources, the absence of thorough test cases was deadly. With my CEO’s support, the project’s stakeholders from marketing and customer service provided numerous and varied test cases with which to confidently unit test my application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-did-i-do-right&#34;&gt;What did I do right?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask myself that every day. I still don’t have an answer. But I still love what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Articles – October 20, 2011</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/articles-october-20-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2011 06:00:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/articles-october-20-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://railscasts.com/episodes/290-soap-with-savon&#34;&gt;#290 SOAP with Savon&lt;/a&gt;
October 17, 2011 &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Articles – October 19, 2011</title>
      <link>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/articles-october-19-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2011 10:42:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.markrichman.com:1313/articles-october-19-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://news.google.com/news/url?sa=t&amp;amp;fd=R&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNHvscyrgvCqzNT8WqvSZZtv1wkx3g&amp;amp;url=http://forwardthinking.pcmag.com/show-reports/289266-gartner-it-s-top-10-technology-trends&#34;&gt;Gartner: IT&amp;#8217;s Top 10 Technology Trends &amp;#8211; PC Magazine&lt;/a&gt;
October 18, 2011 &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>